We truly wish all of our cordial brothers and sisters
We truly wish all of our cordial brothers and sisters
that fullyrs advocate for the restoration.
that fullyrs advocate for the restoration.
Central Surgeon Center responds veryupply
Central Surgeon Center responds veryupply
to the
to the
Paul Davis's discourse.
Paul Davis's discourse.
Pieters perhaps learn about
Pieters perhaps learn about
Welcome to the last feast of knowledge this year
非常歡迎各位來參加本年度最後一次的知識饗宴
So today's speaker, Dr. Lin Jiwen
那麼今天的主講者林繼文博士
Researcher and Director of the Institute of Political Science
是本院的政治學所的研究員兼所長
So he graduated from the Institute of Political Science, Department of Political Science, National Taiwan University?
那麼他是在台大政治系畢業政治研究所嘛
also have
也有
Then, in 1996, UCLA awarded a Ph.D. degree in political science from this branch of the University of California
然後呢1996年UCLA就美國加州羅灘系大學的這個分校的政治學博士
then he is
那麼他是
Taiwan's youth is the most famous political scientist I think
台灣少壯被最有名的政治學家我認為
Then it is the wild lily generation in the broad sense of this wild lily
那麼是這個野百合廣義的野百合世代
Then his greatest interest is to understand why human beings establish norms to limit their freedom
那麼他的最大的興趣是想要了解人類為什麼要建立規範來限制自己的自由
Why do humans establish norms to limit their freedom
人類為什麼要建立規範來限制自己的自由
Is it for greater freedom or for one group of people to dominate another
是為了更大的自由還是為了要一群人要宰治另外
The answer to this question is of course very complex
這個問題的答案當然非常複雜
to answer this question
為了回答這個問題
Dr Lin's Research Interests
林博士的研究興趣
Include the formal model
包括形式模型
including comparative political systems
包括比較政治制度
and East Asian politics
以及東亞政治
and covers abstraction
而且涵蓋了抽象面
Theoretical and local
理論面跟本土面
Professor Lin's academic performance is very good
林教授的學術成績非常的出色
He also passed the National Science Council
他也得過國科會
Contact Home Now
就現在科技部接觸家
Once a modeler of political science
當過政治學門造型人
he has two books
他有兩本書
Papers are published in good Chinese and foreign journals
論文都發表在很好的中外期刊
Including Politics, Journal of Democracy
包括Politics, Journal of Democracy
China Quarterly
China Quarterly
Etc., etc
等等等等
he was a very accomplished political scientist
他是一個非常有成就的政治學者
At the same time, he also endows theoretical thinking
同時他也賦予理論的思考
development of realpolitik
對現實政治的發展
also have very unique insights
也有非常獨到的見解
We have business talks with him every once in a while
我們每隔一段時間就要跟他談商務
Only then do I understand what Taiwan is now
才了解台灣現在在什麼
what's going on in politics
政治在什麼進行
including when we ate
包括剛才吃飯的時候
so that i can understand a little bit
這樣我就稍微有點了解
understand a little bit
稍微有點了解
because i'm a historian
因為我是個歷史學者
history won't run away
歷史不會跑掉
history is always there
歷史往往永遠在那裡
so but politics is different
所以但是政治不一樣
different politics
政治不一樣
politics it has been evolving
政治它一直在發展
inattentive
稍不留神
within a month
一個月裡面
One thing can change Taiwan's political
一件事情就可以把台灣的政治的
Landscape changes it all
Landscape把它整個改變掉
and it's changing very fast
而且改變得非常快
especially now social media
尤其現在社群媒體
Often a thing is not dealt with for a few days
往往一件事情幾天沒有處理
the whole situation changes
整個局勢就變掉
So this gets really fast
所以這個變得非常快
become very fast
變得非常快
so every once in a while
所以每隔一段時間
I'm going to get close
我就要親近幾位
I think the analysis is very accurate
我認為分析非常準確
and theoretically valuable
而有理論價值的
listen to what they have to say
稍微聽聽他們講一講
Then take a look at the political situation in Taiwan
然後掌握一下台灣的政治局勢
And your director is the most important one
而您所長就是其中最重要的一個人
we applaud now
我們現在熱烈掌聲
come and welcome his speech today
來歡迎他今天的演講
Thanks
謝謝
i think i have to introduce myself first
我覺得我要先介紹我自己
This is so-called popular science
這是所謂的科普嘛
Then you should know who I am
那你們應該要認識我是誰
Then I want to introduce Wang Fu just now
然後我要先剛剛王富介紹說
Young Scholars
少壯貝的學者
It's actually very simple because there is no
其實很簡單 因為沒有
So I'm the first and the last
所以我是第一個也是最後一個
because how to say
因為怎麼講
when i got my doctorate
在我拿到博士學位的時候
I was probably the first to run back to Taiwan
我大概是第一個跑回台灣來的
so no one else so simple
所以沒有別人 所以很簡單
ok
好啦
then i want to introduce myself first
那我要先介紹一下我自己
when i was in high school
那我在高中的時候
In middle school and high school
國中高中的時候
my favorite is english class
我最喜歡的是英文課
my favorite is language
我最喜歡的是語言
So I would choose the Department of Politics
所以我那個時候會選政治系
The international relations group is actually very simple
國際關係組其實很簡單
I didn't even think about going into academia
我更沒有想到要去做學術
then i want to be a diplomat
然後我想當外交官
it's easy
很簡單嘛
High school students want to be diplomats
高中生想當外交官
I think being a diplomat is so much fun.
覺得說當外交官實在太有趣了
That was after I entered the political department
那可是我進了政治系以後
I regret the first study
第一個學習就後悔了
why do you regret
為什麼後悔呢
I found Taiwan's diplomacy
我發現台灣的外交
Countries with diplomatic relations are not there
有邦交的國家都不在那裡
my seniors and sisters
我的學長學姐他們
It's just that after entering the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, it's very hard.
就是考進外交部以後都很辛苦
I have a good senior
我有一個很好的學姐
He said you are now in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
他說你現在在外交部
Mr. Li Bin, what are you doing?
李賓師你在做什麼
He said it was hard work
他說很辛苦啊
say what are you doing
說你在做什麼
He said I was opening the menu
他說我在開菜單
what menu
什麼菜單
He said because at that time
他說因為那個時候
we still have a lot
我們還有很多的
that diplomatic relationship is in the middle east
那個邦交國在中東
He said I'm going to notice
他說我就要注意到
The first one is after I open the menu
第一個我菜單開好以後
can't let them see me
不能讓他們看到我
because i'm female
因為我是女性
What about the second one? Those menus are horrible.
第二個呢那些菜單都很恐怖
Anyway, no need to describe
反正就不用形容
You probably know what menu he serves
你大概就知道他開什麼菜單
then he left
後來他就離開
So what I mean is
所以我的意思就是說
The so-called political science is actually quite complicated
所謂的政治學它其實滿複雜
But what we thought at the time
但是我們那個時候的想法
very simple
非常的單純
I just think I'm going to study political science
就是覺得我去讀政治學
I'm going to be a diplomat in the future
我將來就是要當外交官
Later, I found out that this road can't go on.
後來發現說這個路走不下去
Then I passed by
那我後來經過了
Return to Academia Sinica after several years
若干年以後回到中研院
I found that the average person's interest in political science
我發現一般的人對政治學
Still have an interesting idea
還是有一個滿有趣的看法
He said how could political science be called science?
他說政治學怎麼可能叫科學
right
對不對
You should all still have this question now
你們現在應該都還有這種疑問
How can political science be a science
政治學怎麼會是科學
We all know that in the humanities and social sciences
大家知道在人文社會科學當中
will put their own subjects
會把自己的學科
Science is only political science
叫科學的只有政治學
English called Political Science
英文叫Political Science
then nothing else
那其他都不會
What about others?
其他都蠻怎麼講
not so inferior
沒有那麼自卑
because we have to claim we're doing political science
因為我們只好宣稱說我們在做政治科學
The second one is that many scholars
那第二個就是說很多的學者
When you think that political science is not a science
當覺得說政治學不是科學
So just talk about your theory
所以你們的理論就說說就好
ok
ok
That is to say, if politics is not science
也就是說政治學如果不是科學
So you're really like a humanities history?
那你會真的很像人文學歷史學嗎
It seems not
好像也不是
then we are in a very awkward position
那我們就處在很尷尬的狀態
Then I think this impression is still quite deep.
那我覺得這個印象現在還是蠻深刻的
that's talking
那在講
Many people will say, why do you study political science?
很多人他會說那你們為什麼來念政治學
ok
ok
Like my mother asked me what are you studying in political science?
像我媽就問我說你到底政治學在學什麼
If you don't run for president, what are you going to do?
你又不選總統你要幹嘛
ok
ok
I said I was doing learning, how did he do good research
我說我做學問他是怎麼那個什麼好研究的
So now many people's impression of political science comes from Taiwan's education issues
那所以現在很多人對政治學的印象是來自於台灣的教育問題
Because we were divided into two groups in high school
因為我們在高中的時候就分兩組
Wen Group and Li Group
就文組跟李組
Well, we now have research that proves that
那我們現在已經有研究證明說
He showed that in fact the group book of the high school
他顯示說其實那個高中的分組本
is a bad thing
是一個很糟的事情
Why
為什麼
Because it will make the person in the selection team
因為它會讓那個選文組的人
I feel bad at math
覺得自己數學不好
actually that's wrong
其實那是錯的
I remember being very impressed when I was a freshman
我記得我大一的時候印象很深刻
That is to say, among my classmates
就是說我同班同學當中
many people he said
有很多人他說
I finally don't have to study math anymore.
總算不用再念數學了
Many students in the literary group are like this, right?
很多文組學生都這樣對不對
I know many of you feel this way
我知道你們很多人心裡有這種感覺說
Good thing I don't have to study math anymore
好在我不用再念數學了
It gives me a headache to see that loss
看到那一虧險就會頭痛
Many of my classmates are like this
我很多同學是這樣啊
That's why you really want to study political science.
那可是你真的要讀政治科學
you will find a very interesting thing
你會發現一件很有趣的事情
That is to say
也就是說
A topic I want to share with you today
我今天要跟各位分享的一個題目
that is
就是說
How many look here
這邊看起來幾個
sorry
對不起啊
Because I am used to writing in English
因為我習慣就是用英文寫
I'll translate it
我把它翻譯一下好了
so-called political science
所謂的政治學政治科學
with statistics and game theory
跟統計學還有賽局理論
Wait a minute and I'll introduce what game theory is
等一下我會介紹什麼叫賽局理論
what does it matter
到底有什麼關係
OK
OK
so i put the question first
所以我先把問題提出來
mean to say
意思就是說
statistics
統計學
Strategy
Strategy
The most important thing is that game theory is talking about Strategy
最主要是賽局理論在講Strategy
and political science
還有政治學
It's probably the core issue
它大概最核心的問題
authority
問題就受到權威
So what's the relationship between these three?
那這三個到底有什麼關係
Of course you'd think he had nothing to do with it.
你當然會覺得他一點關係都沒有
Actually he has nothing to do
其實他還沒有什麼關係
But I think you look at it from a historical perspective
但是我覺得你從歷史的角度來看
You'll find out that he's not only related
你會發現說他不但有關係
and a very close relationship
而且是非常密切的關係
OK so today I am very
OK 所以我今天一個很
The purpose of the thousand generations is to let everyone know one thing
千輩的目的就是要讓大家知道一件事情
That is to say, political science in the so-called social sciences
就是說所謂的社會科學當中的政治學
The statistics that everyone is talking about now
跟現在大家講的statistics 統計學
game theory
還有所謂的賽局理論
His relationship is very close
他的關係是非常密切
even the closeness of his relationship
甚至於他的關係的密切程度
more than other disciplines
超過跟其他的學科
ok then let's see
好 那我們就看下去
Few people know who this man is
這個人很少人知道他是誰
I was chatting with Deputy Wang when we were eating
我們吃飯的時候我才跟王副在聊
His name is Fal Noyman
他叫做Fal Noyman
John Fal Noyman
John Fal Noyman
So what do you think these three things are related to?
那你說這三個事情有什麼關係
one is to do
一個是做
One is to make yourself very powerful
一個要讓你自己變得很powerful
OK you have a lot to do
OK 你要做很多的事情
Only then can I become a very powerful person
才讓自己能夠變成一個很powerful的人
But you need to understand statistics
可是你要懂統計
then you have to understand
那你又要懂
This Game Theory game theory
這個Game Theory 賽局理論
Maybe I'll think of this guy Fornoyman
大概我會想到這個人Fornoyman
You can't finish the story about Fornoyman
那有關Fornoyman的故事你真的是講不完
he is a very interesting person
他是一個很有趣的人
because he is so famous
因為他太有名了
Inventing new things all the time
一天到晚在發明新東西
so he didn't win any awards
所以他沒有得過什麼獎
ok
ok
one of his most famous examples
那他最有名的一個例子
of course that means
當然就是說
if you have heard
如果你各位聽過
The so-called bland project H Bomb
所謂的清淡計畫H Bomb
he is a very important person
他是一個非常重要的人
ok
ok
He's in a light plan
他在清淡計畫當中
Fornoyman he probably played
Fornoyman他大概扮演了
very important role
非常重要的角色
Then what
然後呢
Does he have anything to do with statistics?
他跟統計學有沒有關係
I need you to check his academic background
有你去查他的學術背景
Of course he's had some experience with statistics.
他當然有碰過統計學的問題
because he's a mathematician at heart
因為他本質上是一個數學家
There must be a problem with statistics
一定會碰過統計學的問題
So you're saying what does he have to do with game theory?
那你在說他跟賽局理論有什麼關係
should say so
應該這樣說
If we take Fornoyman's name off
我們如果把Fornoyman的名字拿掉
no light in game
沒有清淡在賽局
so he's so funny
所以他太有趣了
Because he is in many fields
因為他在很多的領域
he is the founder
他都是開創者
But what?
可是呢
because of him
因為他
The real interest is actually mathematics itself
真正的興趣其實是數學本身
So like Game Theory for him
所以像賽局理論對他來講
just a novel
只是一個小說
He went to write a book when he wrote about it
他寫一下的時候去寫了一本書
It has something to do with the game we are talking about today.
就跟我們今天講的賽局有關係
Fornoiman
Fornoyman
That's why he died young
那可是他很年輕就過世
when i died
我是幾歲就過世
Why
為什麼
Because he participated in the light program
因為他參加清淡計劃
so at that time
所以那個時候
Scientists of about the same generation as him
跟他差不多同一輩的科學家
probably die earlier
大概都比較早死
I didn't have that feeling at that time
那個時候還沒有那個感覺
It means that you participate in the light program
就是說你參與清淡計劃
It's actually a very dangerous thing
其實是非常危險的事情
so he died early
所以他很早就過世
OK so Fornoyman
OK 所以Fornoyman
then we have to look through him
那我們要透過他來看
Are these three things related?
這三個東西的關係嗎
So I asked a question below
所以我下面問了一個問題
that is
就是說
statistics
統計學
Match
賽局
politics
政治學
just rely on such a person
就是單靠這樣一個人
can we link it together?
就可以連起來嗎
the answer is of course no
答案當然是不是的
because this is a very interesting person
因為這是一個很有趣的人
we can connect it
我們可以把它連起來
Then we will now look at the relationship between these three
那我們現在要看這三個的關係
i think it should
我覺得應該
From the next point of view
從下一個角度來看
where does statistics come from
統計學從哪裡來
we want to ask a historic question
我們要問一個歷史性的問題
I deliberately inserted the answer first
我故意把答案先插掉
OK what is the answer
OK 這個答案是什麼
take a look
大家看一下
let me ask you a question first
我先問各位一個問題
what is statistics in english
統計學的英文是什麼
you know
都知道嘛
Statistics in English is statistics
統計學的英文是statistics
Have you ever thought
那大家有沒有想過
What does this statistics mean
這statistics是什麼意思
this word is very long
這個字很長
and very convoluted
而且很繞口
right
對不對
it's there
它在那個
The current Latin is called statisticoon
現在的拉丁文叫statisticoon
it's the same
它一樣就是
from statistics
從statistics
extend out
延伸出來
have you ever thought
你們有沒有想過
Why is it called statistics
為什麼叫statistics
ok now tell everyone
好 現在告訴各位
because it's math for politics
因為它是做政治的數學
So statistics
所以statistics
is to measure your country
就是測量你的國家
so it's political science
所以它是政治學
from political science
從政治學開始
OK, many people think that
OK 那很多人覺得說
how could this be
怎麼會是這樣
we hear now
我們現在聽到
Statistics seem to be
統計學好像都是
what mathematicians are doing
數學家在做的
How to start with political science
怎麼會從政治學開始
have you ever thought about this
有沒有想過這個問題
Look at the book below that was published in 1663
你看下面這個1663年出版的這本書
就是The Nature and Political Observations upon the Bill of Mortality
就是The Nature and Political Observations upon the Bill of Mortality
Its author is called John Grunt
它的作者叫John Grunt
Published in 1663
1663年出版
This is probably the first
這個大概是第一本
The first book compares contemporary
第一本把比較當代
The more modern concept of so-called statistics
比較現代的所謂的統計學的概念
wrote it out
把它寫出來的
what does it talk about
它談什麼東西
it's about nature and politics
它談的是自然與政治
Mortality from the point of view of nature and politics
從自然與政治的觀點看死亡率
If you do demography or statistics
如果各位做人口學或是做統計學
maybe you should know
也許你應該知道
John Grunt is very important
John Grunt這個人非常的重要
We can imagine that in 1663 in
我們可以想像1663年在
when is china
中國是什麼時候
Late Ming Dynasty Early Qing Dynasty
明朝末年清朝初年
is there such a person
有沒有這樣的人
seems difficult
好像很困難
but he has written a
但他已經寫了一本
everyone noticed
大家注意到
One of his keywords is Political
他的一個關鍵字是Political
so it becomes
所以就變成說
The word statistics at the beginning
一開始統計學這個字
originally political science
本來就是政治學
then the first
然後第一本
Comparing modern approaches to writing statistics
比較用現代的方法來寫統計學
This book of statistics
統計學的這個著作
It has a word called Protocolic
它就有一個字叫做Protocolic
So stop saying that political science is not science
所以大家不要再說政治科學不是科學
because statistics comes before all science
因為統計學在所有的科學進來之前
it starts with political science
它是先從政治學開始
I'm really kidding
那我實在在開玩笑
I said statistics
我就說統計學
we all know now
我們現在都知道
The most basic concept of statistics is that
統計學最基本的概念就是說
you have a mother
你有母體
right, there is a mother body
對不對 有個母體
Then I sampled from the matrix
然後我從母體當中抽樣出來
Then I'm going to look at the sampling process
然後我要看看這個抽樣的過程
is it random
是不是隨機的
So I just take a thousand more samples
所以我就只要抽一千多個樣本
I can infer
我就可以推論
Infer what the mother's body is likely to be like
推論母體大概是什麼樣的狀況
You may have thought of one thing
大家可能想過一件事情
Where was statistics first used?
統計學最開始是用在什麼地方
population
人口
what is population in english
人口的英文是什麼
It's called Population
就叫Population
Do you understand?
大家了解嗎
That is to say, we now say that the matrix
也就是說我們現在說母體
Actually sorry to say
其實不好意思講
It originally meant population
它原來的意思就是人口的意思
then i will tell you a story
那我就跟各位講一個故事
that is
就是說
Let me tell you one
先講一個
In fact, there is no concrete evidence to show the story
其實沒有具體證據顯示的故事
but i think it should be like that
但是我想應該是那個樣子
think about it
大家想想看
in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries
在十五十六世紀
fifteenth and sixteenth centuries
十五十六世紀
who is interested in that
誰有那個興趣
who has that resource
誰有那個資源
To find out how many people he managed
去了解他管了多少人
king
國王嘛
Then what
然後呢
he will want to say
他一定會想說
How can I use the lowest cost
我如何可以用最低的成本
minimum cost
最小的成本
To know how many people I have here
去知道我有多少的人口在這邊
what to do
要做什麼
to war
要戰爭
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
because you look like
因為你像看
Europe in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries
十五十六世紀的歐洲
basically in the
基本上就是處在
in a state of war
相互戰爭的狀態當中
then you can think of one thing
那你可以想一件事情
that is to say this thing
就是說這個事情
a king
一個國王
He can know how many people he has
他能夠知道他到底有多少人
can fight
可以爭兵
how much tax can he collect
他可以抽多少稅
so as not to cause riots
才不會引起反亂
That way he's more likely to win
這樣他就比較有可能會贏
So he hates war
所以他是要仇視戰爭
so you know what to say
那所以你就知道說
The concept of statistics
一開始統計學這個概念
In fact, he is in the modern country
其實他是在現代國家
in the process of forming
形成的過程當中
a very strong false
一個非常強的虛假
that is, if I could know
就是說我如果能夠知道
if i could know
我如果能夠知道
what method do i use
我用什麼樣的方法
can maximize my benefits
能夠極大化我的效益
I have a chance to win
我就有贏的可能
So you can immediately imagine a thing
所以你馬上可以想像到一件事情
That is to say, what do these kings do?
就是說這些國王他做什麼事情
i'm imagining
我在想像
Maybe this existed in some time and space very early
可能這個很早就存在了某一些時空當中
What he does is actually very simple
他做的事情其實很簡單
For example, I brought my Dacheng
比如說我把我的大成找來
Find 20 Dacheng
找20個大成來
He said you should at least go now
他說你們現在起碼去
to my territory to see
到我的領土去看
what to see
看什麼 看
how many people do you see
你看到多少人
And you can't two people go to the same place
而且你不能兩個人去同一個地方
right he might have a map over here
對不對 他可能會有一個地圖在這邊
when the time comes you will look around
到時候你們就到處去看
Then you take what you see
然後你們把你們看到的事情
come back and talk to me
回來跟我講
That process is called random sampling
那個過程叫做隨機抽樣
OK, so random sampling means
OK 所以隨機抽樣的意思就是說
You see the population I rule
你去看我統治的population
This is called the motif
這個叫母題
OK then you sample it yourself
OK 然後你就自己去抽樣
come back and report to me
回來報給我聽
the one who can do it
那能夠這樣做的人
He actually has a higher chance of winning.
他其實他贏的機率是比較高
OK so everyone understands
OK 這樣大家了解嗎
That is to say, statistics, he actually
就是說統計學他其實他
His origin is not mysterious at all
他的起源一點都不神秘
He was measuring your territory
他本來就是在測量你的領土
OK
OK
let me say it again by the way
那我順便再講一下
Let's talk about that later
這個等一下我們再講那個
John Grunt's story
John Grunt的故事好了
the book he wrote
他寫的這本書
He is studying the death of the population of London
他是在研究倫敦的人口的死亡
That's because there was a very important issue happening in London at the time.
那因為當時倫敦發生一個很重要的問題
called meaning
叫屬意
Interested
屬意啊
So he called Protocol Observations
所以他叫Protocol Observations
Which means you have to give him a political observation
也就是說你要給他一個政治上的觀察
Why
為什麼
Because I was very interested in such research at the time
因為當時對這樣的研究非常的有興趣
because you think about being a king
因為你想想看作為一個國王
He's actually in Chouse II
他事實上是在Chouse II
Huse II
Chouse II
That British history itself is very complicated
那個英國歷史本身又很複雜
But the king of England at that time was called Chouse II
但是他當時的英國的國王叫做Chouse II
II
二世
Then there is a great need for someone to do this kind of research
那就非常需要有人做這樣的研究
Why
為什麼
Because mortality is probably the foundation of a regime
因為死亡率大概就是一個政權的根基
if your rule
如果你的統治底下
your population is dead
你的人口都死掉了
what do you rule
你要統治什麼
so the first thing he does
所以他要做的第一件事情
Is it possible to pass through
就是能不能夠透過
Such research to understand why people die
這樣的研究來了解為什麼人會死
Or these British subjects below us
或說我們底下的這些英國的臣民
What is the average life expectancy
到底平均壽命有多少
So he must be using statistics
所以他一定是用統計學
He must be using statistics
他一定是用統計學
and then tell my readers to say
然後告訴我的讀者說
How much is our mortality rate the first
我們的死亡率是第一個有多少
For example, how many people in a thousand people will die?
比如說一千個人當中有多少個人會死
for what reason
因為什麼原因
And then of course this involves his investigation.
然後這當然要牽涉到他的調查
Then I can also describe
然後我也可以去描繪
For example, the average population of the city of London at that time
比如說當時的倫敦市的平均人口的
What is the life expectancy
壽命大概是多少
So this is a very important work
所以這個是一個蠻重要的著作
downground
downground
That
那
Of course later
當然後來
This matter was followed by other scholars.
這件事情就被其他的學者接著做了
The statistics we now know better
那我們現在比較了解的統計學
Actually it was later
其實是後來的事情
But he started out to find out where you rule
但他剛開始是要了解你統治的地方
so the other day i heard that kurpi
所以前幾天我聽到那個柯皮
He said something that I found quite interesting
他講一件事情我覺得蠻有趣的
He said there would be no governance without statistics
他說沒有統計就不會治理
nothing wrong
沒有錯嘛
because he is a doctor
因為他是一個醫生
statistics are important
統計學很重要
Like you don't even know you're in
比如說你根本不了解你在
rule where
統治什麼地方
You don't understand how you manage it
你不了解你怎麼去治理它呢
there's nothing wrong with that
這是沒有錯
Well, then of course it means
好 那後來當然就是說
We are more impressed by these
我們比較有印象的這些
Theoretical development with statistics
跟統計的理論發展
Of course the mathematicians are starting to creep in
當然就是數學家開始慢慢進來
For example, there are quite a few famous people mentioned here.
比如說這邊講了好幾個人都滿有名的
For example, one of the most important theories
比如說當中一個最重要的理論
Chance of course
當然就是機率
probability
機率
Probability is of course a mathematical concept
那機率當然是一個數學的概念
But you see these people are quite famous
但是你看這些人都還滿有名的
For example, Baskar and Xianglan
比如說巴斯卡爾跟湘蘭
That's the one
就是那個
Do you know, Ferma?
大家知道嗎 費瑪
should have listened
應該有聽
Is there a math department here?
這邊有沒有數學系的
Institute of Mathematics
數學所
dare not speak
不敢講
OK OK
好了 好了
ferma is famous
費瑪很有名
Of course these are mathematicians
當然這些都是數學家
Then what
然後呢
Look at that Gauss again
再看那個Gauss
Namely CF Gauss 1794
就是說CF Gauss 1794年
that his
那他的
knowledge of statistics
統計學的知識
That is to say, he builds on a foundation
就是說他建立在一個基礎上面
He said
他說
when people have to decide
人要做決定的時候
must face uncertainty
一定會面對不確定性
So we're going to find a
所以我們要找到一個
The most rational decision-making model
最合理的決策的模式
is to minimize
就是要極小化
face uncertainty
面對不確定性
This is a fundamental of statistics
這是統計學的一個基本
this concept
這個概念
That is to say, there must be errors in our statistics.
就是說我們統計一定會有誤差
If you see a paper next time
如果你下次看到一篇paper
It's my sampling with no error at all
它是我的抽樣完全沒有誤差
don't you believe
你不要相信
ok statistics biggest job
ok 統計學最大的工作
is to minimize our error
就是要極小化我們的誤差
but there must be errors
但一定會有誤差
Okay, let's take a look at this guy first.
好 那我們先來看一下這個人
This is John Brown
這個叫做John Brown
this is a very interesting person
這個是一個滿有趣的人
He is a Fellow of the Royal Society
他是英國皇家學會的院士
He had the Royal Society
他那個時候就有皇家學會
That's why he wants to be an academician
那可是他要當院士
This thing is taken by many other
這件事情是被其他很多
Fellows of the Royal Society object
皇家學會的院士反對
Why
為什麼
Have you ever thought about this question
大家有沒有想過這個問題
please teach me
請教一下
why do you think he was opposed
你覺得他為什麼會被反對
you don't know him well
你跟他不熟
you say you don't know
你說你不熟
you say you say
你說你說
not yet
還沒有
Only he will have statistics in the future
只有他以後才會有統計學
no that book sold well
不會 那本書賣得很好
for what reason
到底因為什麼原因
Have you ever thought about this question
大家有沒有想過這個問題
you hurry up
你這 趕快趕快
so and so
誰誰誰
just speak louder
就講大聲一點
ok then we should find out
好 那我們應該去了解一下
What were the fellows of the Royal Society doing at the time?
當時的英國皇家學會的院士在做什麼事情
I don't have an answer to this right now
這個我現在沒有答案
I don't know. Going to investigate
我不知道 要去調查一下
out of line
當道不合
very good
很好
This is a political interpretation
這個是一個政治性的解釋
is there any other explanation
還有沒有其他的解釋
It's about Newton
跟牛頓有關啊
should be ok
應該沒有關係
but this is fun
但是這個很有趣
Newton's era should be about the same as his
牛頓的時代應該跟他差不多
Yes, but Newton, the founder of the Royal Society, was a little bit older than him.
對 但是皇家學會創始人牛頓比他早一點點
is there any other answer
還有沒有其他的答案
this is very interesting
這是很有趣的
The first person to write a book on statistics
第一個寫書 寫統計學的書的人
Why him? Will he object to his entry into the Royal Society?
他為什麼 他進英國皇家學會會不會反對
Why did he enter the Royal Society?
他為什麼要進英國皇家學會
yes
是
he and he is not considered scientific
他跟他是不是被認為是科學
In fact, he also saw that you had a Publication at that time.
其實他那個時候也是看你有Publication
Right? People with good publications are more likely to
對不對 那你Publication好的人就比較可能
then you are probably right
那你講的大概是對的
Do you know what his identity is?
大家知道他的身份是什麼嗎
Soldiers, at that time many people were called Captain
軍人 那個時候很多人都叫Captain
Below are some Captains
下面有一些Captain
And then it's over, he's an interesting identity.
然後講好了 他身份很有趣
he is in the sales department
他是在賣部的人
Because their family moved to London later
因為他們家後來搬到倫敦去了
His father is a businessman
他爸爸就是一個部商
That is to say, if you want to make clothes, you need to find his father.
就是說你要做衣服的話 就要找他爸爸
so he is a businessman
所以他是一個businessman
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
Then he didn't have any high education
然後他沒有受過什麼很高的教育
that's interesting that is to say
那很有趣就是說
He certainly inherited his father's trade
他當然繼承他父親的行業
He is also a salesman
他也是一個賣部的人
because we think he's weird
因為我們覺得他很奇怪
I want to ask Mr. Wang Hu about this
我想問一下那個王沪議員這樣
Is it possible that such a person would come out in China at that time?
在當時的中國有可能這種人會出來嗎
unlikely right
不太可能對不對
Very difficult
很困難
Even in the UK, he is opposed by many people
那即使在英國 他也是被很多人反對
That is to say, how can a businessman enter the Royal Academy?
就是說一個部商怎麼可以進皇家學院
I don't know that our traditional Chinese medicine hospital is of course much better now.
我不知道我們現在中醫院當然好多了
But I don't know why the British Royal Academy at that time had such
但是我不知道當時的英國的皇家學院為什麼會有這種
He was actually discriminated against, simply put, discriminated against
他其實是被歧視 簡單來講被歧視
Then a friend just mentioned why he went in later, do you know?
那剛剛有一位朋友提到說他為什麼後來進去你知道嗎
I don't know about this, I don't have any evidence, I can't just talk about it
這個我不曉得 我沒有證據 不能隨便亂講
but that book is selling well
但那個書是賣得很好
It is because the current Chos'a second recommended him to say
就是因為當道Chos'a second推薦他說
you want to let him in
你要讓他進去
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
So it's not that he doesn't fit in with the Dao, but he fits in with the Dao
所以他不是跟當道不合 是跟當道很合
This is good, politics is always there
這個好 政治永遠都在那邊
That is to say, your relationship with the leader actually has a little influence.
就是說你跟當道的關係 其實才有一點影響
So this is a pretty interesting story
所以這個是一個蠻有趣的故事
That is to say, we look at it from the perspective of historical eyes
就是說我們從歷史的眼睛的角度來看
The development of fellow economics, of course he has his
同濟學的發展 當然他有他的
The actual demand is quite strong
現實的需求蠻強的
Then we saw that the word classmate was meant to measure your country
然後我們看到同學這個字本來就是在測量你的國家
And then the first statistics textbook was kind of like this thing
然後第一本統計學的教科書有點像是這個東西
In fact, he was talking about politics.
其實是他在講的是政治這件事情
He talks about Mortality
他講Motality
If he wants to enter, the Huang Family Academy will not be able to enter.
那他想進 黃家學院也進不去
But because Chalster II appreciates his
可是因為Chalster II滿欣賞他的
That is to say, you must let him in, and he will go in.
就是說你一定要讓他進去 他就進去了
So of course he has a little influence on the later research
那所以他當然對後面的研究是有點影響
We are now reading about the life cycle
我們現在在讀那個生命週期這件事情
should read this guy
應該都會讀到這個人
But his real identity is a cloth seller
可是他真正的身份是一個賣布的人
OK so I think it's a funny thing
OK 所以我覺得這是一個很有趣的事情
Let's look at this question again
我們再來看下面這個問題
Now let's talk about these three things separately.
那我們現在先把這三個東西分開講一下
that's next
那在接下來
We want to say that this is what statistics look like
我們想說統計學就是這個樣子
What is the so-called game?
那所謂的賽局到底是什麼東西
In fact, the game theory should not be complicated
賽局理論其實大家不要把它想得很複雜
'Cause we're playing games every day
因為我們天天都在玩賽局
OK, for example, if you are older, you can play mahjong
OK 比如說年紀比較大一點打麻將
play poker
玩撲克
the younger man
那比較年輕的人
Maybe as soon as December 31st someone wants to play a board game
可能快到12月31號有人要玩桌遊
right
對不對
human beings as long as they live
人類只要活著
Everyone wants to play some games
大家都會想到去玩一些遊戲
In fact, it is called Game Theory, which means game theory.
其實它叫 Game Theory 本來就是遊戲理論的意思
It is more clearly called Spill Theory in German
它德文講得更清楚叫 Spill Theory
Spill means to play
Spill 的就是玩的意思
So it's not so mysterious
所以它本來就沒有這麼神秘
So we think of it ourselves as if
所以我們自己把它想得好像
like something we don't understand
好像是我們不懂的東西
It's not that mysterious
其實沒有那麼神秘
it means to say
它講的意思就是說
when we make a decision
我們在做決定的時候
If I have several options to choose from
如果我有好幾個方法可以選
why i choose this method
我為什麼要選這個方法
unselective method
不選別的方法
isn't it simple
這不是很簡單嗎
now game theory
那現在賽局理論
The funniest thing about it is
它最有趣的地方是
When I'm thinking about what method I'm going to use
當我在想我要用什麼方法的時候
You should also consider what other people are thinking
你應該還要考慮到別人在想什麼
right
對不對
Because a really good player
因為真的很厲害的玩家
You must have thought of this
應該都會想到這件事情吧
That is to say, if I play this card now
就是說我如果現在打這張牌
then will you follow
那你會跟嗎
or you will have better cards
還是你會有更好的牌
right
對不對
People who are more good at playing should think about this.
比較會玩的人應該都會想這件事情
Then I often discuss with my mother
那我就經常跟我媽在討論
playing mahjong
打麻將這件事情
I feel really great
我就覺得真的很厲害
she is very old
她年紀很大了
but still played well
可是還是打得很好
She said you really have to know how to play mahjong
她說你真的要會打麻將
You must know what the other three are thinking
你一定要知道其他三家在想什麼
or you will lose
要不然你就會輸掉
this is really awesome
這真的太厲害了
that means
那意思就是說
a person who is actually making decisions
一個真正在做決定的人
He not only has to consider his own interests
他不但要考慮他自己的利益
consider his own position
考慮他自己的立場
Not only should he consider
不但要考慮到他覺得
What kind of decision is better for him
什麼樣的決定對他比較有利
His considerations should include what others are thinking
他的考慮應該包括別人在考慮什麼
so everyone can understand
這樣大家可以了解嗎
So when it comes to Game Theory
所以講到Game Theory
It is actually a core concept
它其實是一個最核心的概念
called Common Knowledge
叫做Common Knowledge
is the consensus
就是共識
what is consensus
什麼叫共識
it's me thinking what are you thinking
就是我在想你在想什麼
I know what you're thinking about me
我也知道你在想我在想什麼
So when I'm thinking about what you're thinking
所以當我在想你在想什麼的時候
i know you know
我知道你也知道
i know what you're thinking
我知道你在想什麼
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
You know what I'm talking about when you do this
這件事情你做起來就知道我在講什麼
but it means
但是它意思就是說
when i was thinking what is the best solution
我在想什麼是最好的解的時候
I must take into account
我一定要考慮到
What are others thinking about this solution?
別人在怎麼想這個解
Well, this is actually what we do in our daily life.
那這個其實就是我們在日常生活當中
a frequently encountered situation
經常碰到的一種狀況
Is this good?
這樣做好嗎
OK, for example, during the election
OK 比如說選舉的時候
Do you think typing this negative text now
你覺得現在打這個負面文
or he is helpful to you
還是他對你有幫助
Then you send negative WeChat
那你打負面微訊
He must have thought of how the other party would fight back.
他一定應該想到對方會怎麼樣的回擊
is when you take everything into consideration
就是你把所有的東西都考慮進來以後
Maybe that's a thing they call equilibrium
也許那個就是一種他們叫均衡的東西
so
所以
Strategy跟calculation
Strategy跟calculation
This thing was meant to be put together
這件事情本來就是放在一起
Then I want to remind you one word
那我要提醒大家一個字
called Strategy
叫做Strategy
OK because when we say
OK 因為當我們說
when we are playing a game
我們在玩一個遊戲的時候
The method I choose is called Strategy
我的選擇的方法叫做Strategy
According to Julien
按照朱利倫的講法
what does he call strategy
他叫什麼東西是戰略
what is his name
他叫什麼
I remember he seemed to call it a strategy or a strategy
我記得他好像把它叫做戰略還是策略
His is Chao Abe's three strategies
他那個就是超安倍的三策了
Anyway
Anyway
what
什麼東西
ok ok
OK 好啦
In fact, his English is Strategy
他其實英文就是Strategy
Strategy is an interesting concept
Strategy它是一個很有趣的概念
Let's say I'm telling you now
比如說我現在跟你講說
The game is studying Strategy
賽局在研究Strategy
That is to say, I know several strategies
就是說我會好幾個策略
English is called strategy
英文叫strategy
Actually, the first thing you think of is political science.
其實你第一個想到的就是政治學
right
對不對
The most care in political science is strategy
政治學最care就是strategy
Economics is not very good at speaking this word
經濟學還不太會講這個字
But one of the almost central problems of political science is that
可是政治學幾乎核心的問題之一就是
where is your strategy
你到底你的戰略在哪裡
You should now be able to find some links
那各位現在應該可以找到一些連結點
That is to say, why was there statistics in the first place?
就是說剛開始為什麼會有統計學
Because national defense requires war
因為國防要戰爭
how do you win the war
戰爭你要怎麼贏
In addition to your data to be correct
除了你的data要正確以外
You also need to know what the other party is going to do
你還要知道對方要幹什麼
that's called strategy
那個叫戰略
so early on
所以早期的時候
these things just go together
這些東西根本就搞在一起
good
好
let's see the next one
我們再看下一張
So when it comes to this so-called game theory
那講到這個所謂的賽局理論
i want to mention him a little bit
我要稍微提一下他
when we just ate
我們剛剛吃飯的時候
Still talking to the vice president about this person
還是在跟副院長在談到這個人
Called Thibis Nash
叫Thibis Nash
On the left is when he was younger
左邊那是他比較年輕的時候
On the right is when he won the award
右邊是他得獎的時候
But during this time
但是中間這一段時間
The vice president should be invited to introduce him
應該請副院長來介紹他
Ask Nash to meet them
叫Nash跟他們見過面
should have met
應該是見過面
his story is very very wonderful
他的故事非常非常的精彩
If you are interested
那你們如果有興趣的話
you can go to him
可以去找他的
It should be someone else helped him write the album
應該是別人幫他寫的專輯
It's called A Beautiful Mind
叫做A Beautiful Mind
beautiful mind
美麗的心靈
very well written
書寫得非常的好
what kind of man would nash be
那將Nash是什麼樣的人
who we are reading the innings of now
我們現在在讀賽局的人
There's probably no way you don't know Nash's name.
你大概不可能不知道Nash這個人的名字
Why
為什麼
Because your equilibrium is called Nash
因為你的均衡就叫做Nash
if you take Nash off
如果你把Nash拿掉的話
you don't know what you're doing
你就不知道你在做什麼
So now we are looking for something every day
所以我們現在天天都在找一個東西
Called Nash Junker
叫做Nash Junker
Nash means Nash
Nash就是Nash的意思
Then I remember when I was learning the game
那我記得在我學賽局的時候
i asked my boss
我有問我的老闆
When did Jiang Nash die?
江Nash什麼時候過世
He said there is no death
他說哪有過世
why didn't he write paper
他為什麼都沒有寫paper
Shouldn't he write a lot of papers?
他不是應該寫很多paper嗎
Then you go to see his doctoral dissertation
那你去看他的博士論文
He originally wrote his doctoral dissertation
他博士論文他原來寫
Hearing and writing three pages
聽說寫三頁
Later he was too embarrassed to tell him
後來他不好意思跟他講
don't just write three pages
不要只寫三頁
Later he wrote him in twenty-one pages
後來他把他寫成二十一頁
You can still download now
現在還可以download
maybe hit his name
也許打他的名字
It should be possible to connect to download his doctoral thesis
應該可以連到去download他的博士論文
That doctoral dissertation is very well written
那博士論寫得非常的好
his most important contribution
他最重要的貢獻
The so-called Naschic Lubeum
所謂的Naschic Lubeum
Naschic Lincoln
就是Naschic Lincoln
from his doctoral dissertation
就是從他的博士論文來的
OK, that's John Nash.
OK 好 那John Nash這個人
himself his story is full of drama
他本身他的故事充滿了戲劇性
when he was already very famous
當他已經非常的有名了
After about 30 years old
以後大概30歲以後
He has Skytophrenia
他有Skytophrenia
just have schizophrenia
就是有精神分裂
OK, of course I heard that Princeden is very nice to him.
OK 那當然聽說Princeden對他還滿好的
So he was in Princeden for a long time
所以他很長一段時間就在Princeden
In 1994, he was to be awarded the Norbert Prize in Economics
到後來1994年要頒Norbert經濟學獎給他
see how long it takes
看中間有多長的時間
so he is a very important person
那所以他是一個非常重要的人
So why is John Nash so important?
那John Nash為什麼這麼重要
he has a little story
他有一個小故事
That is to say, the person he most admires
就是說他最崇拜的人
It's the first photo
就是前面第一張照片
Fornoiman
Fornoyman
Why
為什麼
because Fornoyman was in Princeden at the time
因為當時Fornoyman也在Princeden
Institute for Advanced Study
高等研究院
So he always wanted to
所以他那個時候一直想讓
The great John Fornoyman had an impression of him
那個偉大的John Fornoyman對他有印象
because he's just a young guy
因為他只是一個年輕小伙子
go to doctoral class
去讀博士班
he knows why
他知道他為什麼
Why did he choose Prince instead of Harvard?
他為什麼選Prince的沒有選哈佛
'Cause Prince's got these freaks over there
因為Prince的有這些怪咖在那邊
Einstein that Fernoyman
Einstein 那個Fernoyman
It's these freaks from Europe
就是這些從歐洲去的這些怪咖
i just forgot to say
我剛剛忘了講
That is to say, Jiang Fernoyman
就是說那個江Fernoyman
He is a Hungarian Jew
他是匈牙利的猶太人
he is complicated
他很複雜
not very complicated
不是很複雜
Said his family affairs are complicated
說他的家事很複雜
what game did he play when he was a kid
他小時候他做什麼遊戲
his daddy would put his daddy as a banker
他的爸爸會把他爸爸是銀行家
just call him
就把他叫來說
Come now you make a game for
來 現在你做一個遊戲給
my guest see
我的客人看
Come on, here is a phone book, right?
來 這邊是一本電話本對不對
then you start watching now
那你現在開始看
Watch it, cover it up
看好了 蓋起來
Come on, you recite their phone numbers
來 你來背他們的電話號碼
I think it's best not to let my kids play this kind of game
我覺得最好不要讓我的小孩玩這種遊戲
scary
很恐怖
he is a genius
他是一個天才
Then for Jiang Nash to let
那他為了 江Nash為了要讓
that's what they call
他們就叫這樣
It just came to my mind
這樣才忽然想到
That is to say, in order to impress Jiang Fernoyman
就是說他為了要讓江Fernoyman有印象
He went to discuss math problems with him
他去跟他討論數學問題
but heard
可是聽說啦
I heard that Jiang Fernoyman could not bear to dump him
聽說江Fernoyman不勝甩他
He was greatly stimulated
他受到滿大的刺激
I did the game before and I did the game
我之前做賽局我也做了賽局
So he later wrote his national books
所以他後來就把他國書都能寫出來
that this is a short story
那這個是一個小故事
But I know that between these mathematicians
但是我知道這些數學家之間
they have some really weird connections
他們有一些非常奇怪的連結
But then of course because he wrote
可是後來當然因為他寫了
The so-called National Collibion
那個所謂的National Collibion
become famous
就變得很有名
OK so famous we don't even know where he is
OK 有名到我們都不知道他人在哪裡
but he is very important
那但是他是很重要的人
But certainly no John Nash without Fanolimne
但是沒有Fanolimne當然也不會John Nash
They are actually linked
他們事實上是有連結關係
Well this is John Nash
好這個是John Nash
Then let's talk a little bit about the last topic.
那再接下來我們再把最後一個題目稍微講一下
The so-called political science in the institute
那所謂的政治學在研究所
Now back to the core question of political science
現在回到政治學的核心問題是什麼
The core problem is probably Power
核心問題大概就是Power
Power
Power
But how many words are there that are very similar to Power?
那但是呢跟Power很類似的有幾個字
Do you want to talk about it here?
要不要講一下這邊
Closer to Power
跟Power比較接近
related to power
跟權力比較有關係
Authority
Authority
authority power
權威 權力
that is not that force this force
那個不是那個力 這個力
is the power of that power it does not
是那個力量的力 它也沒有
ok then let me tell you
好吧 那我就來講一下
Authority it is a very interesting state
Authority它是一個很有趣的狀態
its essence is violence
它的本質是violence
what is violence
什麼叫violence
It's just that I can make you not want to do this thing
就是我可以讓你不想做這件事情
I must let you do this
我非讓你這樣做不可
if you don't want to
如果你不願意這樣做
I can restrict your freedom
我可以拘束你的自由
To put it bluntly, I can lock you up
再直接一點就是我可以把你關起來
that's what it means
就是這樣的意思
OK, of course I can use many other methods
OK 那我當然還可以用很多種方法
to restrict you from doing something
來限制你做一些事情
So it's essentially a violence
所以它本質是一個violence
So its violence means
所以它的violence就是說
I know you really don't want to do such a thing
我知道你非常不想做這樣事情
But I force you to do such a thing
可是我強迫你一定要做這樣的事情
Okay, so why can Authority be compared with violence?
好啦 那為什麼Authority可以跟violence點起來
Because there is a process in it
因為它中間有個過程
OK it's a power
OK 它是一種power
what is power
那什麼叫做power
power and the force that general economists talk about
power跟一般經濟學家講的那個force
a little different
有點不一樣
power means
power的意思就是說
if i say now to you
如果我現在比如說我對你
If I don't have power for you
我對你沒有power的話
I'm not sure if you'll listen to me
我不能確定你是不是會聽我的話
so it has a mandatory meaning
所以它有強制性的意思
power means mandatory
power是有強制性的意思
so its core
所以它的核心
Because it is essentially relying on violence
因為它的本質上是靠著violence
so it will have power
所以它會有power
But what's interesting about it is that it says
但是它有趣的地方在於說
it will tell you
它會告訴你
people who use power will tell you
使用權力的人會告訴你
I use this power because
我用這種power是因為
I have a legal process
我有一個合法的過程
so it is
所以它是
Planning to be publicly desirable
Planning to be publicly desirable
Which means I did it to you because
也就是說我這樣做對你是因為
I have to look out for the interests of the majority
我要照顧大多數人的利益
example
舉例啦
or if I don't
或是說如果我不這樣做
i may be other
我可能會被其他的
Like things like destroyed by power
比如說力量所摧毀之類這樣的事情
so this is a very interesting feeling
所以這個是一個很有趣的感覺
what is authority
什麼叫做authority
authority it must imply power
authority它一定隱含著power
The base of power is violence
那power的base就是violence
so you need to know
那所以你要知道
These concepts are related
這幾個概念是相關的
then let's see
那我們再來看
the front side
前面那邊
good
好
let's think again
那我們再來想
That is to say, under what circumstances
就是說什麼樣的狀況底下
what kind of situation
什麼樣的狀況底下
We don't need Authority
我們不需要 Authority
this is an interesting question
這個是一個很有趣的問題
We just said Power is important
我們剛剛說 Power 很重要
We can't imagine saying a government has no rights
我們不能想像說一個政府沒有權利
but you think backwards
但是你倒過來想
what kind of situation
什麼樣的狀況底下
We don't need Power
我們不需要 Power
You ask an economist and he'll tell you
你去問經濟學家他會告訴你
why would he tell you
為什麼他會告訴你
Because he said at least when I was young
因為他說至少我小時候
When I was a freshman
我以前大一到的時候
Learn that individual economics, he told you
學那個個體經濟學他告訴你
the market is perfect
市場是完美的
invisible hand
看不見的手
This sentence is really good
這句話實在講得太好了
I can’t even see my hands, how can there be Power
手都看不見了怎麼會有 Power
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
economist at least
經濟學家至少
I studied economics at that time
我那個時候學的經濟學
he told me
他告訴我說
The Greatest Economist
經濟學家最偉大的地方
just an invisible hand
就是有個看不見的手
telling us what to do
在告訴我們要做什麼事情
OK, what is the invisible hand?
OK 什麼叫看不見的手
You have no idea where Power is
你根本不知道 Power 在哪裡
Of course there are some market rules
這當然有一些比如說市場規則
Under a certain market rule, you really can’t see it
到了某一種市場規則底下的確你看不見
There are market forces
有市場的力量
But there are still many places in our human life
可是我們人類的生活當中還是有很多的地方
not only hands can see
不但手會看得見
and he wants you to see
而且他要讓你看見
OK
OK
If you see you ignore me
你如果看見你還不理我
I will use the next step
我就會用到下一步
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
So the human phenomenon is very complicated
所以人類的現象很複雜
But economists are less likely to talk about this
但是經濟學家比較不會談這個東西
because they want
因為他們很希望
The final order of the market is when it is invisible
最後的市場的秩序就是看不見的時候
dominating everything
在主宰一切
OK
OK
So if you use game theory to solve these problems in economics
所以如果你用賽局理論來解經濟學的這些問題
you will have a problem
你會碰到一個問題
So what
So what
I figured it out for a long time, if the final result is what will happen naturally
我解了半天如果最後的結果就是自然會發生的
Why do I use the game to solve it?
我幹嘛用賽局來解
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
You can of course predict an equilibrium
你當然可以去predict一個均衡
Then this equilibrium is that everyone
然後這個均衡就是每一個人
he only for himself
他只要為了自己
pursue the best interests
追求最大的利益
society as a whole will achieve the greatest benefit
整個社會就會達到最大的利益
Right
對吧
It seems that many economists still think this way
好像很多經濟學家現在還是這樣想
But for the time being, economists believe
但是 暫時說 經濟學家相信
I also admit that there is such a world
有這種世界我也承認
But it's not all of the world
但是這不是世界的全部
if your game is really interesting
如果你賽局真的有趣的話
you should imagine a situation
你應該想像一種狀況
is when I'm looking for my best interest
是當我在追求最大利益的時候
I will cause inconvenience to others
我會對別人造成很不方便的結果
Only in this way will there be power
這樣才會有power
That's why this power says you can't do this
所以這個power才會說你不可以這樣做
right? that's what it means
對不對 這個才是說
If this matter is beneficial to everyone
這件事情如果對大家都有利
but it's not what you want
可是不是你要的
then i can ask you to do this
那我可以要你一定要這樣做
That is to say we are gamers
就是說我們在做賽局的人
will realize a very fundamental problem
都會意識到一個很根本的問題
our individual rationality
我們個體的理性
collective irrationality
可能是集體的不理性
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
That is to say, of course we personally can pursue
就是說我們個人當然可以追求
your own interests
你自己的利益
But you have to see what the result is
可是你要看這樣做的結果是什麼
Could be a disaster for the collective
可能對集體來講是一個災難
Of course I'm not talking about all social actions
當然我不是說所有的社會行動
or society's choice must be
或社會的選擇都一定是這樣
But we cannot rule out the possibility
但是我們不能排除這種可能性
is ubiquitous
是普遍存在的
wait a minute we'll see
那等一下我們會看
Where does this possibility exist?
這種可能性到底存在在什麼地方
ok now let's see
好 現在我們就來看
These three things we now fill it up
這三個東西我們現在把它填起來
The first of course is to say
第一個當然就是說
From the origin of history
從歷史的起源來看
We will now give you a brief summary
我們現在幫各位做一個簡單的摘要
That is, the reason why statistics
就是說 之所以會有統計學
because some people
是因為有一些人
He is in the process of building the modern nation
他在建立現代的國家當中
Need to know where his population is
需要知道他population在哪裡
this is not a simple question
這個不是一個簡單的問題
We now think that this problem is too simple
我們現在想這個問題就是太簡單了
Let's do a national census
我們就來做一個全國的普查
Just think about how it was possible 400 years ago
你想想看400年前怎麼可能
it's very very difficult
這是非常非常困難的事情
So who can figure it out first
所以誰能夠先想出來
A better way to estimate
一個比較好的方法去估計
OK, how many people do I rule?
OK 我統治的人到底有多少人
then i can count
那我才能算啊
How many adults can serve in the military?
算多少成年人可以去當兵啊
When I calculate more accurately
我算得比較精準的時候
If the opponent is not sure, I may win him.
對方算不準我就可能會贏他
So just started his origin
所以剛開始他的起源
Indeed, because some people
的確是因為有一些人
In the process of forming modernity
他在形成現代性的過程當中
he needs to get to know people
他需要去了解別人
OK that's the fundamental reason
OK 那是最根本的理由
I'm going to find out who I rule over
我要去了解我到底統治了誰
second what do i do
第二個我要做什麼事情
usually for war
通常是為了戰爭
Don't forget it's the book
大家不要忘記就是那本書
the one just mentioned
就是那個剛剛講到
The book The Nature and Political Observations
The Nature and Political Observations那本書
it 1663
它1663年
what is the significance of 1663
1663年有什麼重要性
1663 you are going to push forward
1663年你要去往前推
In 1648, a very important concept came out
1648年有一個非常重要的概念出來
modern state
叫做現代國家
Do you understand?
大家了解嗎
Modern State
Modern State
We now use the watershed of the modern state
我們現在用現代國家的分水嶺
Probably Vesuvalia 1648
大概就是1648年Vesuvalia
How to say in Chinese
中文怎麼講
kyphalia
Cifalia
that's it
是這樣講
Cifalia system
Cifalia體制
is what we see now
就是我們現在看到的
Actually Europe
其實就是歐洲
The embryonic form of that time
那個當時的這個雛形
probably
大概就是
It is Vesuvalia
就是Vesuvalia
that meeting
那個會議
it's set out to say
它訂出來就是說
we are doing international politics now
我們現在在做國際政治
do international relations
做國際關係
you need to know
你要知道
We still follow this system
我們還是遵循了這個體制在走
As far as Modern State
就Modern State
So it's probably around the same time
所以它大概是在同一個時候
so it's realistic
所以它的現實的
That is to say, when the modern state is already in the process of forming
就是說 當現代國家已經在形成的過程當中
At this time, there will be conflicts between countries
這個時候國家跟國家之間會有衝突
Then your conflict could lead to war
那你衝突就可能引發戰爭
Then you start a war who will win
那你引發戰爭誰會贏
because he is modern
因為他有現代性
So he must have used the so-called scientific method
所以他一定是用所謂科學的方法
If I can use the minimum cost
我如果能夠用最小的成本
Estimate how many people I can rule
估計出來我可以統治多少人
how much food can i smoke
當中我可以抽多少的糧食
OK how many adult males can I send to the battlefield
OK 我可以送多少的成年男性去戰場上
Then he won't report to the police
然後他不至於去報動
he's more likely to win
的話 他比較有可能會贏
Of course I know that human beings have always had this need
當然我知道說人類一直都有這樣的需求
But when Europe has become a system of modern states
可是當歐洲已經變成現代國家的體系的時候
We need to know that at this time he has a very intense competitive pressure
我們要知道這個時候他有一種非常激烈的競爭壓力
The strange thing is
很吊詭的事情是
Of course science has a chance
當然科學有出來的機會
Because modernity inherently has a characteristic
因為現代性本來就有一個特質
called scientific
叫做科學性
This is the system
本來就是這樣的體系
So from the perspective of historical development
所以從歷史的發展來看
We know that the statistics come out
我們知道說統計學的出來
related to acts of war
跟戰爭行為是有關
So he must have something to do with politics
所以他一定跟政治學是有關
ok then let's talk
好 那我們再說
From the essence of these three theories
從這個三個理論的本質上來看
Does it have some correlation
它有沒有一些相關性
Then I think today this
那我覺得今天這個
this is what i really want to talk about
這個是我真的要講的東西
Tongji
就是說同濟學
Games and Politics
賽局跟政治學
what is its relevance
它到底有什麼相關性
OK
OK
I think you can start thinking about this now
我覺得這個大家現在已經可以開始思考
Why do we three things tie it together
為什麼我們這三個東西要把它綁在一起
no way to take it apart
沒有辦法把它拆開
so we can now
所以我們現在可以
Take these three things a little
稍微把這三件事情稍微
rephrase
rephrase一下
we will say
我們會說
because there are three dots
因為有三個點
right
對不對
statistics game politics
統計學 賽局 政治學
Then we just said
然後我們剛剛已經說了
If you go through game theory
如果你透過賽局理論
when your forecast is invisible
你的預測是看不見的時候
then why do we need games
那我們為什麼需要賽局
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
game theory
就是說賽局理論
Began to become influential to economists
開始變成對經濟學家有影響
It's because people don't believe that time
就是因為大家不再相信那一次
out of sight
看不見的時候
Right
對吧
This should come naturally
這應該很自然可以了解
He told you that I let you see every day
他告訴你我天天讓你看見
so the country becomes important
所以國家變得很重要
So game theory he actually told us that
所以賽局理論他其實告訴我們說
There are some things that constantly need someone to do it
有一些事情是不斷的需要有人來操作
Can't really believe in the invisible
不可以真正的相信看不見的
so we now know
所以我們現在知道
That is to say, politics has something to do with the game.
就是說政治學跟賽局是有關係的
let me ask you another question
那我再問各位一個問題
What is political science? Have you ever thought about it?
什麼叫政治學大家有沒有想過
I forgot to ask you this question
我都忘記問各位這個問題
yeah so i'm going to ask you now
對 所以我現在要問你
I'm kidding everyone
我跟各位開一個玩笑
I remember my freshman year
我記得大一
When I was a sophomore, I took a class
大二的時候我去上一堂課
The teacher will ask you a question
老師就問你一個問題
What do you think is the difference between politics and economics?
你們覺得政治學跟經濟學差別在哪裡
You should know economics
你經濟學應該知道吧
what is economics
經濟學是什麼
is there another point
那有沒有其他一點
Which one do you think is more important
你覺得算哪一個比較重要
The way resources were just allocated
剛剛分配資源的方式
any left
還有沒有
all good
好 都很好
Do you have any other comments?
還有沒有其他的意見來講
Ok, Ok
可以 可以
Well, this definition is very good
好 這個定義非常的好
Let's come back to this definition later
等一下我們再回到這個定義
just over there
剛剛那邊
good
好
Then the answer I heard at that time
那我那個時候聽到的答案
scare me
讓我嚇一跳
what is economics
它什麼叫經濟學
economics first
先講經濟學
Economics is easier to understand
經濟學比較容易了解
economics is in
經濟學是在
With limited resources
資源有限的狀況底下
For your resources
對於你手邊的資源
for the best reason, right?
做最好的理由 對吧
because it must have a condition
因為它一定有一個條件
i.e. your resources
就是說你的資源
not infinite expansion
不是無限擴張
Just under this given condition
就在這個給定這個條件底下
The reason you do the best with resources
你對資源做最好的理由
right?
沒有錯吧
probably acceptable
大概可以這樣接受
Then the politics are exactly the same
然後政治學一模一樣
really
就真的
True learning is to make the best use of limited resources
真學是在資源有限的狀況底下做最好的利用
Aren't these two disciplines the same?
這兩個學科不是一樣嗎
Zhenxue plus two words
真學加兩個字
Make the best use of the limited resources of others
對別人有限的資源做最好的利用
This is the fundamental difference between the two disciplines
這個就是這兩個學科基本上的差別
Why does the government tax
政府幹嘛要抽稅
Didn't we start off by saying it's taxpayer money?
我們不是先在講說這是納稅人的錢嗎
yes
對啊
so he needs to rationalize
所以他需要合理化
He said that if there is no tax collection, there will be problems in society.
他說不抽稅這社會會出問題
so you just have to pay him taxes
所以你就只好交稅給他
do you really not pay taxes
你真的不交稅嗎
waiting behind waiting for you
等著後面在等你
So political phenomena must be compulsive
所以政治現象一定有強迫性
So why would he follow some political science
所以為什麼政治學他會跟一些
such as ethics
比如說道德規範
would even say that a large part of political philosophy is discussing this issue
會跟甚至於說政治哲學有一大部分在討論這個問題
How the state can justify its coercion against you
國家如何可以合理化他對你的強迫
ok, this is a very big difference between political science and economics
ok 這是政治學跟經濟學一個非常大的差別
But in essence, it is the best use of resources
可是本質上都是對資源做最好的利用
just one is its own resource
只是一個是自己的資源
one is someone else's resource
一個是別人的資源
just kidding
就是彈開玩笑講
alright
好了
we now return to political science
我們現在回到政治學
Political science, in fact, we just talked about it like this
政治學它其實我們剛剛這樣講
game theory
就是說賽局理論
if it's going to be useful
它如果要有用處的話
In fact, it should be more useful for political science
其實應該對政治學是比較好用
Why
為什麼
Because its core concept is strategy
因為它的核心觀念就是strategy
what is strategy
什麼叫strategy
strategy means that it is at your hand
strategy就是說在你手邊
For example, in the case of three sides
比如說三側的狀況底下
which one do you think is more important
你覺得哪一個比較重要
Right
對吧
Then you said that the public funds should be included in the basic public funds
那你說要讓公資在基本公資
It's better to raise it to 30,000 yuan
漲到三萬元比較好
or to solve other problems first
還是要先解決別的問題
something like this
類似像這樣的東西
That is to say, you have to choose a strategy
就是說你要做策略的選擇
And each strategy choice
而且每一種策略選擇
may have to be considered
可能都要考慮到
Will the other party
對方會不會
For example, the basic salary is increased to 30,000 yuan.
比如說基本公資漲到三萬元
Will there be some adverse effects
會不會有一些反效果
issues such as
之類的問題都要去考慮
OK
OK
this is a link
這是一個連結
then ask
那請問一下
What is the relationship between politics and statistics?
政治學跟統計學有什麼關係
yes
沒錯
Just one relatively capable
就一個比較capable
Of course he hopes that his current decision is based on an objective basis
他當然希望他現在的決策是建立在客觀的基礎上面
right base above
正確的基礎上面
So one thing we need to know is that
所以我們要知道一件事情就是說
sorry
對不起
When the concept of statistics began to be accepted by everyone
當統計學這個概念開始被大家接受的時候
The first will apply statistics
第一個會運用到統計學的
In fact, it is a government agency
其實就是政府機關
OK is a government agency
OK 就是政府機關
Because he feels his rule must be based on a proper understanding of the society I control
因為他覺得他的統治必須建立在對我所控制的社會的正確瞭解上面
let's talk backwards
我們倒過來講
If there are some governments when he doesn't actually do that
如果有一些政府他其實沒有這樣做的時候
In fact, his life span will be shorter
其實他的壽命會比較短
because you're not building on the right foundation
因為你沒有建立在正確的基礎上面
OK so he might be wrong
OK 所以他決策可能是錯的
OK so we know
OK 所以我們知道的
Then there is another line that I want to talk about today.
那還有一條線就是我今天想講的
So what is the relationship between game theory and statistics?
那請問一下賽局理論跟統計學有什麼關係
right
對不對
We have drawn two lines
我們已經畫了兩條線
one more line
還有一條線
What do you think is the relationship?
大家覺得有什麼關係
Let's look at it from the concept of paying money
那我們從出錢的概念來看
we would feel like saying
我們會覺得說
The so-called Game Theory, it predicts what you will do
所謂的賽局理論他預測你會做什麼行動
Does statistics try to predict the condition of the mother with the least cost?
那統計學是盡量的要用最小的成本去預估母體的狀況是什麼嗎
So what's the relationship between these two?
那請問一下這兩個有什麼關係
would you like to talk more
你要不要講多一點
I'd love to hear your answer let me have a sip of water
我很想聽聽你的答案 讓我喝一口水
The mayor was in the defense plane, did he ever execute
市長在國防機裡面他是不是曾經是施行
Game isn't it?
賽局不是嗎
Mayor, you and Luo Fa were locked up during the entire operation
市長你跟羅發在整個行為的關在
so what do you do
所以你對於什麼行為
Fu Yu Lun you agree
富裕倫你贊成
I ask Fu Yulun in front of you if you agree
我問前面這個富裕倫你贊成
alright
好啦好啦
Well, I think it's all right
那其實我覺得都可以
I think someone who has an opinion
我覺得一個誰有意見的
Actually, I think you've got the answer to your question.
其實我覺得你講到問題的答案
we are in this world
我們在這個世界
The most important thing about modernity is that I'm anxious
現代性最重要一件事情就是我很焦慮
so i must win
所以我一定要贏
do you understand what i mean
你瞭解我的意思嗎
Previously people may not have this state
以前的人可能不會有這種狀態
but modern is
可是現代是
it will tell you one thing
它會告訴你一件事情
This is a competitive society
這是一個競爭的社會
you want to survive
你要能夠存活下去呢
you are about to win
你就要贏
something you know to win
什麼東西你知道要贏
OK, the worst I have ever seen is the students in Singapore
OK 我看過最慘的就是新加坡的學生
He is worse than Taiwanese students
他比台灣學生還要慘
Because they have been divided into classes since childhood
因為他們從小就有分班
For EM1, EM2, EM3
就EM1、EM2、EM3
that's not mysterious at all
那個一點都不神秘
What are EM1, EM2, EM3
什麼叫EM1、EM2、EM3
E is for English
E就是English
M is for Mathematics
M就是Mathematics
So you get a grade from a young age
所以你從小就會受到一張成績
but your ranking in all singapore
但是你在全新加坡的排名
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
I don't know if that's the case now
我不知道現在是不是這樣
But they are very competitive
但是他們的競爭性是很強的
His EM3 ​​person
他那個EM3的人
He already told you from primary school
他就已經告訴你從小學開始
Said you are the person from EM3
說你就是EM3的人
So his system is very
所以他那個體系是非常
It's actually pretty scary
其實蠻可怕的
But he is based on statistics
但他是建立在統計學上面
but tell you
可是告訴你
You are among the children in Singapore who are all grade 1
你在全一年級的新加坡的小朋友當中
where do you rank
你排第幾
that pressure is very high
那個壓力非常的大
I want to say that I will definitely be there
那個我想說我在那邊一定會
will win you soon
一定會趕快贏你
This to his immigrant in a sea of ​​people
這向他的移民以處人海
what i'm trying to say is
我要講的意思就是說
There is a system that does it like this
有一種體系是這個樣子做
But even if you don't have such a system
可是你就算沒有這樣的體系
The characteristic of modern society is, of course, that
現代社會的特性當然就是
except in a competitive environment
除在一個競爭環境
in a very intense society
非常激烈的社會當中
Everything is ranking
什麼東西都在比排名
And I'm just talking about one thing
而且我光講一件事情
That is to say, the concept of time
就是說所謂的時間的概念
part of modernity
是現代性的一部分
People in the past were not so precise
以前的人沒有這麼精確
Tell me what time, minutes and seconds
說現在到底幾點幾分幾秒
you see i've been looking behind
你看我現在一直在看後面
what time is it
到底現在幾點幾分
because i have to do the next thing
因為我要做下一件事情
so when your time is being
所以當你的時間被
when cut into very precise units
切割成非常精確的單位的時候
All your stuff will come from here
你所有的東西都要從這邊來
measure your price
衡量你的價格
not value but price
不是價值是價格
So of course modernity has a characteristic
所以現代性當然有一個特徵
which means you'll be in a competitive situation
就是說你會處在競爭的狀態
That's why I say that in fact statistics started
所以我才會說其實統計學一開始
It is in the process of modern state competition
就是在現代國家競爭的過程當中
There are some people who want to use the lowest cost
有一些人他想要去用最低的成本
to get the best estimate
去得到最好的估計
aim is to win
目的是為了要贏
what is winning
什麼叫贏
To win is to beat the opponent
贏就是打敗對方
so i know say
所以我知道說
There is a link like this
有這樣的一個連結
But what is the relationship between statistics and games?
可是統計學跟賽局的關係是什麼
Has anyone thought about this
有沒有人想過這個問題
I wish you didn't say that last sentence
你沒有講最後這句話就好了
no i feel close
沒有 我覺得很接近
very close
很接近
never mind
算了
what is your major
你的專業是什麼
your business department
你的業務理系
I think it makes sense
我覺得很有道理
that is
就是說
Anyway, for most people
反正對大多數人來講
You can't understand the paper of the game or the paper of statistics
你看賽局的paper跟看統計學的paper都看不懂
ok
ok
joke
開玩笑
In fact, what you said is probably substantive.
其實你講到大概是實質的
But it has one fundamental difference
可是它有一個基本的差別
That is to say, through game theory,
就是說你透過賽局理論
The predictions you are making are decisive
你在做的預測是決定性的
deterministic
deterministic
right
對不對
it will tell you which strategy is best
它會告訴你哪一件策略最好
which strategy is best
哪一個策略最好
Right
對吧
For example, I now have three
比如說我現在有三次
Then after my estimation
然後經過我的估算呢
I think the first time might be best
我覺得第一次可能最好
it tells you
它告訴你
first time best
第一次的最好
that's it
那可是呢
when you do statistics
當你做統計學的時候
it won't tell you advice
它不會跟你講的建議
it will tell you
它會告訴你說
Each strategy has its different amount of variation
每一個策略有它不同的變異量
So it has a fundamental difference
所以它有一個基本的差別
one tells you what to do
一個是告訴你應該做什麼
and another one tells you
然後另外一個告訴你
How to Minimize Your Variation
如何極小化你的變異量
or minimize your residuals
或是極小化你的殘差
right
對不對
what do we call
我們說什麼叫做
A good statistical model
一個好的統計學的模型
It can try to make your arrow term
它能夠盡量的讓你的arrow term
The sum of the squares of is the lowest
的平方加起來是最低的
This is called the method of least squares
這個叫做最小平方法
but it won't tell you
可是它不會告訴你
what are you supposed to do
什麼是你應該做的事情
But the game it will tell you
可是賽局它會告訴你
which one is the thing you should do
哪一個是你應該做的事情
then i think you got the point
那我覺得你講到重點
That is to say, these two things
就是說這兩個東西
It's two sides of the same coin
根本就是一體的兩面
when i'm making a decision
當我在做一個決定的時候
I know when I should
我知道我應該這樣做的時候
But who can guarantee you
可是誰可以給你掛保證
Said it must be the best strategy
說這一定是最好的策略
So it must have error
所以它一定會有誤差
So people who do game theory
所以做賽局理論的人
its one of the most troublesome things
它最麻煩的一件事情
That is to say, in fact you look through the mathematical model
就是說事實上你透過數學模型
deduced results
推演出來的結果
is mathematically true
是數學上為真
but actually don't know
但是現實上不知道
But you said that in fact you really don't know?
但是你說現實上你真的不知道嗎
nor
也不是
It will tell you the difference in probability
它會告訴你有機率性的差別
It will say, for example, you choose the first strategy now
它會說比如說你現在選第一策
that should be true
那應該是真的吧
But is it really guaranteed?
可是真的能夠掛保證嗎
You need classmates and scholars to help you
你需要同學學家幫你
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
That is to say, it plays a different role
也就是說它扮演不一樣的角色
one tells you what to do
一個是告訴你應該做什麼
The other one tells you how high the risk of doing this is
另外一個是告訴你這樣做的風險有多高
But I don't think you can take it apart
但是我覺得你不能把它拆開
so it becomes
所以就變成是
When we look at these two disciplines
我們在看這兩個學科的時候
Wait a minute I'm introducing the definition in the middle
等一下我在介紹中間那個 definition
that something
那個什麼東西
When we look at these two disciplines
我們在看這兩個學科的時候
very funny
很有趣
It's just that their tendencies are different
就是他們的 tendency 不太一樣
But the problems they face are actually very similar
但是他們面對的問題其實很像
that is, when we are making a decision
就是說當我們在做決定的時候
what decision is better
什麼決定比較好
It's a matter of game
這是賽局的問題
Another one is to say
另外一個就是說
when we are sampling
當我們在進行抽樣的時候
which sampling method
哪一種抽樣的方式
Which statistical model
哪一種統計模型
can minimize the level of our error items
可以讓我們的誤差項目的平康最少
it equals the way because otherwise the government would offset it
它打平方式因為要不然有政府會抵消掉
OK so it's actually facing the same kind of thing
OK 所以它其實在面對是同樣類似的東西
Then can we find a link between them?
那我們可不可以找到一個他們中間的連結
Let's take a look at the equation in the middle
大家看一下中間那個equation
don't think it's scary
不要覺得它很可怕
It means that this is a Basein thing
意思就是說這是一個Basein的東西
B-A-Y-E-S-I-M Basein Stuff
B-A-Y-E-S-I-M Basein的東西
it's called... let's just call it the back
它叫...我們就把它叫背式好了
Its concept is like this
它的概念是這樣的
That is to say, back statistics should be called back rules
就是說背式統計應該說背式法則
it has a belief
它有一個信念
It's Thomas Base who told us one thing
就是Thomas Base他告訴我們一件事情
Any of our decisions can be based on a Prior
我們任何的決定都可以建立在一個Prior
a bright faith above
一個鮮豔的信念上面
like i think you're good
比如說我覺得你是好的
But are you really good? I want to observe you
可是你真的是好的嗎?我要觀察你
Then I can update based on my observation of you
那我可以根據我對你的觀察來update
renew my beliefs
更新我的信念
That is to say, a person can have his own beliefs about anything
就是說人可以對任何的事情都有他自己的信念
doesn't matter
無所謂
But I can see through my constant observation of you
但是我可以透過我對你不斷的觀察
and make my beliefs closer to the truth
然後讓我的信念比較接近真實
This is not the same as the concept of classical statistics
這跟古典的統計學的概念是不一樣的
OK means that I can make my prior belief through my observation
OK 意思就是說我可以透過我的觀察來讓我的 prior belief
slowly approaching the real situation
慢慢接近真實的狀況
So it must have conditional probability
所以它一定有條件機率
Conditional probability means that
條件機率的意思就是說
For example, we see here
比如說我們看到這邊
That prdT means
那個prdT的意思是
Given T then the probability that D is true
給定T 然後D為真的機率
OK let me talk again
OK 我再講一下
Just the one over here define
就這邊那個 define
This pr means
這個pr 它的意思就是說
prdT means
prdT的意思是
You have to look at the probability of T existence first
你要先看一下T存在的機率
Then look at the probability that T exists
然後看一下T存在的機率當中
part of D
屬於D的部分
How high is the proportion of
所在的比例有多高
OK so you have to give a condition first
OK 所以你要先給定一個條件
Then look at the condition where the condition exists
然後看一下這個條件存在的狀況
Below is the prior belief you are interested in
底下你有興趣的那個 prior belief
what are the chances it's true
它是真的機率是有多高
and what is this on the right
然後右邊這是什麼東西
That's data when you don't have any theory
那個就是你沒有任何理論的時候的 data
So we can define a thing
所以我們可以 define 一個東西
That is to say, you can see the gap between the two
就是說你看這兩者的差距
One is that you don't have any theory
一個是你沒有任何的 theory
Another one is that you have a theory
另外一個是你有一個 theory
Then you have to look at the difference between the two
然後你要看這兩個的差距
Of course we know that the greater the gap between the two
我們當然知道這兩個差距越大
I give a simple example
我舉個簡單的例子
For example, when I was a child, I really liked watching detective decimals.
比如說我小時候非常喜歡看偵探小數
Then I think the most interesting one is of course that Sherlock Holmes
那我覺得最有趣的當然就是那個佛爾摩斯
I heard he's going to act recently, right?
聽說他最近要演對不對
do you want
要嗎
to the UK
對英國的
then i think they
那我覺得他們
Really
真的嗎
OK
OK
i heard there was this movie
我聽說有這部電影
So what I'm trying to say is that
那我要講的意思就是說
I think the most interesting thing about him is telling us what reasoning is
我覺得他最有趣的地方是告訴我們什麼叫推理
Reasoning is actually a very interesting process
推理事實上是一個非常有趣的過程
He tells you that you can see the same things as normal people
他告訴你說一般人你都可以看到同樣的東西
For example, the police can see this thing
比如說警察可以看到這個東西
Detectives can also see this thing
偵探也可以看到這個東西
Then why are their conclusions different?
那為什麼他們的結論會不一樣
That's the interesting question, isn't it?
這才是有趣的問題對不對
That is to say, the data you see is the same
就是說你看到的data都一樣
OK
OK
But what about this
可是呢這個
When a detective doesn't have any theories
一個偵探他沒有任何的理論的時候
He wants to say that's all
他想說就是這樣而已
But Holmes, he can take a closer look
可是佛爾摩斯他就可以仔細看
Looking around, he said OK
看東看西他說OK
This is what a left-handed person does
這是一個左手的人做的事情
why can he do this
他憑什麼可以這樣做
this is an interesting question
這是一個很有趣的問題
why it can be deduced
為什麼它可以推論
Said the case was a left-handed
說這個案子是一個用左手的認作
Because you have to look carefully at the evidence at the scene
因為你要仔細看現場的證物
because it can see something that others also see
因為它可以看到一些別人也看見
But others don't know why
但是別人不知道為什麼的現象
that is a very simple truth
那一個很簡單的道理
That is, if you see a pipe
就是說如果看到一根煙斗
It is, for example, left over from the chest hand
它是比如說這個胸手留下來的
what do you want to see
你要看什麼東西
You want to see which side it burns
你要看它火燒哪一邊
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
So you can immediately generate a chain of inferences
所以你馬上可以產生一連串的推論
If we are right-handed
如果是我們是用右手的
Which hand do I hold the pipe with?
我是用哪一隻手拿煙斗
i don't smoke now
我現在不抽煙
So this example is not good
所以這個例子不好
So you have to know that in the 19th century
所以你要知道在19世紀的時候
everyone smokes pipes
大家都抽煙斗
so you just have to watch which side it burns
所以你只要看它火燒哪一邊
You can make a series of inferences saying
你就可以一連串的推論說
This is a pipe it usually uses
這個是一個它常用的煙斗
it must be left handed
它一定是左撇子
So this thing is
所以這個東西就是說
you see the same thing
你看到同樣的事情
But you because you have a theory
可是你因為有一個theory
say it might be left handed
說它可能是左撇子
Then you see this phenomenon
然後你看到這個現象
later you will carry people
以後你會扛負人
you will carry people's guesses
你會扛負人你的猜測
OK, that so-called powerful detective
OK 那一個所謂的厲害的偵探
He's looking for that tiny piece of evidence
他就找那個微小證據
Because he can find a lot of
因為他可以從現場當中找到很多
Things that most people think are unimportant
一般人覺得不重要的事情
Then he will slowly make his theory true
那他慢慢慢慢的會讓他的理論為真
Say it's not just for lefties
說這個不只是左撇子
and he may be poor
而且他可能很窮
or something like this
之類的像這樣的事情
and he's funny
而且他很有趣的地方
I couldn't understand when I was a child
我小時候看不懂
Now fully understand what he's talking about
現在完全了解他在講
He said that after you rule out the impossible possibility
他說你排除那種不可能的可能性以後
the rest is possible
剩下的就是可能了
This is what Base tells you
這個就是Base告訴你的事情
because when you see a D
因為當你看到一個D的時候
When a Data
一個Data的時候
You have to know that he sometimes comes from T
你要知道他有些時候是來自於T
Right? Your Theory
對不對 你的Theory
But sometimes it comes from not T
可是有些時候也來自於不是T
So you just find the
所以你只要找到說
The chances that he might spawn from something other than T are very low
他可能產生於不是T的機率是很低的
Then you believe he is from T
那你就相信他是來自於T
small T
小T
OK that's a very simple reasoning logic
OK 那是一個很簡單的推論的邏輯
But I think it's very helpful
但是我覺得是很有幫助
That's why I will say next
那所以我下面才會說
that T and D
那個T跟D
Miss T and D
小姐的T跟D
It is probably a Theory and a Data we talked about
大概就是我們講的一個Theory跟一個Data
Your physics department is very good
你這個物理系的特別好
what is experiment
什麼叫實驗
right
對
It is on the computer as long as it is behind the work
就是在電腦上它只要在工作後面
then we can see its secret
那我們可以看它的機密
right
對
just see all the information
就看到所有的資訊
So you can't put it on me
所以說都不能放到我
So it can't be put into the experiment
所以就不能放到實驗
right
對
There is a very important principle in your experiment
你做實驗有一個非常重要的原則
That means you need treatment
就是說你要有treatment
then you must know one thing
然後你一定知道一件事情
You give it treatment and it will generate data
你給它treatment它會產生data
You did not give it treatment it will not generate data
你沒有給它treatment它不會產生data
So PRD is equal to you
所以PRD等於你
do you understand what i mean
你了解我的意思嗎
That is to say, the PRD behind this formula
也就是說這個公式後面那個PRD
it won't generate
它不會產生
because you didn't give it treatment
因為你沒有給它treatment
so the previous one
所以前面那個
The conditional probability is the PRDT
條件機率是PRDT
it is E
它是E
because you give it treatment it will produce
因為你給它treatment它一定會產生
So you are comparing the gap between the two
所以你在比較兩個的差距
when it is equal to E
當它等於E的時候
you just believe it's true
你就相信這種事情是真的
The big t is called truth
那個大的t叫做truth
It can also be called theory
也可以叫做theory
good
好
So this probably means
所以這個大概就是說
We're connecting games with statistics
我們在連結賽局跟統計學
In fact, you can use the concept of a Base
其實你可以用一個Base的概念
connect it
把它連起來
on the one hand
就是一方面
What the game tells you is
賽局告訴你的是
sorry
對不起
What we're doing is a prediction
我們在做的是一個預測當中的
For example, an expectation
比如說一個期待值好了
It is better for you to adopt this strategy at this time
說這個時候你做這個策略是比較好的
But there must be risks
可是呢一定有風險
where does this risk come from
這風險到底從哪裡來
Depends on your previous game
要看你前面那個賽局
Is your inference reasonable?
你的推論到底合不合理
OK so of course we want to say
OK 所以我們當然希望說
The prediction we make is
我們做的預測是
There are some, say, theories
既有一些 比如說一些理論
tell you that you should do this
告訴你說你應該這樣做
do this for you
這樣做對你來講
risk is relatively low
風險是比較低的
What is lower risk
什麼叫風險比較低
that is if you do
就是說你這樣做的話
no objection or anything like that
比較不會有人反對之類的東西
So it's basically two sides of the same coin.
所以它根本就是一體兩面
Then this is the so-called basic link
那這個就是所謂的basic link
Then let's see who this person is
那我們先來看一下這個人是誰
who is base
who is base
You put the photo like this on purpose
你就是故意把照片放成這個樣子
We want because our most important job today
我們要 因為我們今天最重要的工作
It's ancient, right?
是講古 對不對
tell you a long time ago
跟你講 很久以前的人
who is this
這個是誰
Is there anyone studying mathematics here?
這邊有沒有念數學系的
I just asked sorry
剛剛有問過對不起
Did you study math?
有沒有念數學沒有
Then I deliberately put this photo
那我故意放這張相片
Who is that
它是誰
Then let me tell you a very interesting thing
那我跟各位講一件很有趣的事情
This person can't take root in today's society
這個人在現在社會是沒辦法生根
Because his preparation theorem has not been published
因為他的備事定理沒有Publish
his preparation theorem
他的備事定理
As far as the logic of the set of inferences we just talked about
就我們剛剛講的這一套推論的邏輯
after he died
是他死了以後
After he died, his friends helped him gather
死了以後他朋友幫他集結
and then tell everyone
然後再告訴大家說
In fact, apart from the fact that he is actually doing those things,
其實他除了他真的在做那些事情以外
Then this is a very interesting theorem
然後這個是一個很有趣的備事的定理
So he can't root now
所以他現在是沒辦法生根
The question is what did he do?
那他問題是他到底做了什麼事情
What exactly are his other books?
他其他的著作到底是什麼
have you ever thought about this
有沒有想過這個問題
Okay, let me reveal to you
好啦 跟各位揭曉一下
Most of his writings are on theology
他大部分的著作是寫神學
Many people find it strange
那很多人覺得很奇怪
because the pastor of the presbyterian church
因為長老教會的牧師
Pastor of the Presbyterian Church in England
英國的長老教會的牧師
And he's probably older than Grant
然後他的年紀大概比將Grant
a little younger
稍微年輕一點點
Probably an English Presbyterian priest in the early 18th century
大概是18世紀初的一個英國長老教會的牧師
it's fun to let him talk
讓他講下去就很有趣
Because why there are Presbyterian churches in the UK
因為英國為什麼會有長老教會
Because of course it has something to do with the Civil War in England.
因為當然跟英國的內戰有關
You can't finish the story of the English Civil War.
你講到英國內戰的故事講不完
let's not talk today
今天先不講
i mean
我的意思就是說
he is a pastor of a church
他是一個教會的牧師
Presbyterian pastor
長老教會的牧師
so his real job is preaching
所以他真正的工作是傳道
Then why did he come up with the must be theorem?
然後他為什麼會搞出必是定理這個東西
Have you ever thought about this
你們有沒有想過這個問題
And I heard you tell me a very interesting thing
而且我聽各位講一件很有趣的事情
that is to say his name has been around for a long time
就是說他的名字有很長一段時間
people don't know
人家不知道
Live to the last ten years
到最近十年開始活
If you are going to take a statistics class now
你現在如果你要去修統計學的課
You need to see if he is teaching back statistics
你要看說他是不是在教背式統計
Back-style back is his dead back
背式的背就是他背死
Then we do the game a little earlier
然後我們做賽局稍微早一點
But after 1980, there was a game called back game
但1980年以後就有一個叫背式賽局
What is a back game?
什麼叫背式賽局呢
mean to say
意思就是說
You can see your opponent's actions later
你可以看到你的對手的行動以後
you will renew your belief in who he is
你會更新你對他是什麼人的信念
It's natural, right?
這很自然嘛 對不對
For example, I see you are weird
比如說我看你怪怪的
Just check what you say and watch what you do
就是查其言觀其行
After seeing you for a while, I feel
看你一陣子以後覺得
You're supposed to be one of those things that I hate.
你應該是我很討厭那種的之類的
He wants you to see the current information
就他要讓你看現在的資料
Why is he in statistics
為什麼他在統計學
In the last ten years, the fire has started again
到了最近十年再開始火候
because it requires a lot of calculation
因為他需要大量的計算
require a lot of calculations
需要大量的計算
Only then can you update your beliefs
才能夠去update你的信念
Then why does a vision think of this thing?
那為什麼一個目識會想到這件事情
Because that reason is very simple
因為那個道理非常的簡單
you know what to say to him
你就知道說對他來講
God is invisible, right?
上帝是看不見的對不對
God is of course invisible
上帝當然是看不見的
But what?
可是呢
God will let you see
上帝會讓你看見
things you can see
你可以看見的東西
this is interesting
這就有趣了
That is to say, you are an invisible body
就是說你一個看不見的本體
he will let you see
他會讓你看見
things you can see
你可以看見的東西
so you as a believer
所以你作為一個信仰者
You can see signs of God every day
你可以每天都看見上帝的跡象
So your Vision means this
所以你的Vision就是這個意思
If you are always in this state
如果經常處在這種狀態當中
you will renew your beliefs
你會更新你的信念
belief in faith
就是信仰的信念
It's just that he mathematicalized this thing
只是他把這個東西數學化來
so
所以
Probably no one wanted to publish it at the time
可能當時也沒有人要出版這個東西
But he did write down his theories
但是他是有把他理論寫下來
So be with him as a
所以跟他作為一個
Presbyterian pastors are closely related
長老教會的牧師是有很密切的關係
because you since you can't see
因為你既然你看不見
then why should you trust him
那你為什麼要相信他
That's because he let you see some
那是因為他有讓你看見一些
visible things
可以看見的事情
OK good
OK 好
So this is Thomas Space
所以這個就是Thomas Space
That
那
he is he must feel very strange
他是他一定覺得很奇怪
Why after 200 years
為什麼經過了200多年
suddenly began to thicken
忽然開始變得厚厚
good
好
Finally, let's talk about a small problem
最後我們再講一個小小的問題
that is
就是說
how do we research
我們到底要怎麼研究
Research
研究
Authority
Authority這件事情
We say that the essence of Authority is
我們說Authority的本質就是
How do I make the best use of other people's resources
我如何對別人的資源做最好的應用
right
對不對
Then how to study him on this matter?
然後這件事情怎麼去研究他呢
This is of course the so-called political science
這當然所謂的政治學裡面
There are many, many, many self-domains
有很多很多很多的自領域
For example, of course some of us care
比如說我們當然有些人關心
process of legalization
核法化的過程
Some people care about legitimacy
有人會關心什麼叫正當性
But we are also interested in saying
但是我們也有興趣說
Do it as a subject of empirical research
把它當做一個經驗研究的課題來做
What is empirical research?
什麼叫經驗研究呢
we need to understand
我們要了解到
For example, this country
比如說這個國家
This government has a policy now
這個政府它在現在有一個政策
Since the government is pushing this policy
然後既然是政府在推這個政策
it must be compulsive
它一定有些強迫性
So we're going to ask the fundamental question
所以我們就會問一個根本的問題
does it do this well
它這樣做好嗎
what is good and bad
什麼叫好跟壞
becomes something that can be measured
就變成一個可以測量的東西
OK so we definitely need to know a few things
OK 所以我們一定需要了解幾個事情
The first is to say
第一個就是說
what is the advantage of it doing so
它這樣做的好處在哪裡
where is the disadvantage
壞處在哪裡
Can the benefits and disadvantages be measured?
好處跟壞處可以被測量嗎
It would be fun if it couldn't be measured
如果不能測量那就很有趣了
That's different
那就是各說各化了
OK
OK
Although I know that politics often differs
雖然我知道政治上經常各說各化
But if it's on research
但是如果它在研究上面
It's all over
各說各化就完蛋了
turns into saying it doesn't have a consistent standard
就變成說它沒有一個一致的標準
So there are some topics it can actually
所以有一些題目它其實可以
to understand
去了解說
What is the source of the so-called authority?
所謂的權威的來源到底是什麼
How many people does it benefit
它到底是讓多少人得到利益
OK of course we know no
OK 我們當然知道沒有
a policy
一個政策
It should be said that the policies that most governments are promoting
應該說大部分政府在推的政策
more or less limited dissatisfaction
多多少少都會有限不滿意
Limited will be satisfied
有限會滿意
Then we have to measure
那我們就要衡量說
How many satisfied people are there?
這個滿意的人到底有多少
How many people are dissatisfied
不滿意的人大概有多少
So this probably means
所以這個大概就是說
How do we study authority
我們怎麼樣去研究 authority
Let me tell you this example
我現在講這個例子給各位聽
Then this is a very, very famous case
那這個是一個非常非常有名的賽局的 case
very very simple
非常非常的簡單
let me say by the way
我順便講一下
That if you are interested
那個如果你們有興趣啊
Interested in Game Theory
對賽局理論有興趣
You can next year on May 15th
你們可以明年的5月15號
Attend a lecture at the Department of Political Science, National Taiwan University
去台大政治系聽一堂課
That is Teacher Lin Zhemin
那個叫做林哲民老師
The topic he opened is called president
他開的題目就叫做 president
crime problem
求犯難題
Mr. Lin Zhemin is in our building now
那林哲民老師他現在在我們大樓
He is a graduate of the Department of Electrical Engineering
他是電機系畢業
Then why did he study political science?
那為什麼他去讀政治學呢
He shouldn't think the electrical engineering department is boring
他應該不是覺得電機系無聊
He should feel that the problem of political science
他應該是覺得政治學的問題
funnier than a motor
比電機有趣
Then why is he so obsessed with this matter?
然後他為什麼會非常的著迷這件事情
presence dilemma
presence dilemma
because he said it was a very simple model
因為他說這是一個很簡單的模型
let's take a look
我們看一下
We use this thing as a game theory case
我們就用這個東西當作一個賽局理論的case
Let's look at this below
我們看一下底下這個
this thing
這個東西
Let's say there are two people
我們說現在有兩個人
Two people
兩個人
Then each person has two strategies
那每一個人他有兩個策略
one called
一個叫做
copyrightCooperate with each other
copyright跟對方合作
The other one is called defect
另外一個叫做defact
defact means not to cooperate with the other party
defact也就是說不要跟對方合作
So the strategy of the two people is the same
所以兩個人的策略一樣
and what are those numbers in the middle
然後中間這些數字是什麼
The numbers in the middle are your payoff
中間這些數字就是你的payoff
The higher the number, the better
數字越高代表越好
so it's easy
所以很簡單吧
What we're going to look at now is to say
我們現在要看的就是說
These two people if he
這兩個人如果他
itself has two strategies
本身有兩個策略
Do you want to cooperate with each other?
要不要跟對方合作
Do you want
要不要
Then each state has four states, right?
然後每一個狀態有四種狀態對不對
Two to one two equals four
二成一二等於四
Each state will give you some points
每一種狀態會給你一些分數
Then we now know that
然後我們現在知道說
these two people
這兩個人
Of course he just wants to get the highest score
他當然就是希望自己拿到最高的分數
it's easy
這很簡單吧
then what would you choose
那請問一下你會選什麼
I should cover this first
我應該先把這個遮起來
No, there are three here
不行這邊有三個
Can't hide
遮不掉
Actually I should do an experiment
其實我應該做實驗
Don't ask, let's see who you will choose
不問看大家你會選
So this story turned out to have been written a long time ago.
那這個故事它原來是很早就已經有人把它寫出來
But who turned it into something that everyone can understand
但是是被誰把它變成大家都聽得懂的東西
It's John Nash's teacher
就是John Nash的老師
Just John Nash in front of him, his teacher
就前面那個John Nash他的老師
Because he turned it into a story that everyone can understand
因為他把它變成一個每個人都聽得懂的故事
What is this called? It's called a quarantine certificate
這叫什麼呢?叫隔離證詢
OK now suppose there are two suspects
OK 現在假設有兩個嫌疑犯
they robbed the bank
他們去搶了銀行
After being arrested, the police said whether they did
然後被捕以後警察就說有沒有做
So cooperation means I say I didn't do it
所以合作的意思就是我說我沒有做
To betray the other party is to say that he has done it
出賣對方就說他有做
The policeman is quarantine
那警察是隔離證詢
So he can ask the same question to two people
所以他可以對兩個人問同樣的問題
OK so what do you think your strategy is
OK 那你覺得你的策略是什麼
Do you want to betray each other?
要不要出賣對方
you think you're gonna betray
你覺得你會出賣對方
I'm asking if anyone is nice
我問一下有沒有人很好的
Then you don't want to betray the other party's
然後你不想出賣對方的
just talk
就講啊
Otherwise I can't go on
要不然我講不下去了
You will have someone who doesn't want to betray the other party and choose the cooperate
你會有人不想出賣對方就選那個cooperate
How about, okay, hypothesize like this
要嘛 好啦 這樣假說
Let's say you don't sell out
假說你不要出賣對方
make you feel where your risk is
讓你覺得你的風險在哪
You'd think you'd be betrayed by him, wouldn't you?
你會覺得你會被他出賣對不對
Do you understand where my problem is?
大家了解我的問題在哪裡嗎
That means you're going to wonder if he's going to betray me
就是說你會想說他要不要出賣我
if i don't betray him
如果我不出賣他
The premise is that he must not betray me
前提是他一定也不可以出賣我
But do you really believe he won't betray you?
可是你真的相信他不會出賣你嗎
no why
不會 為什麼
this is human nature
這是人性
but i want to tell you
但是我要跟各位講
The basis of this human nature is the calculation of the game
這個人性的基礎就是賽局的計算
let me tell you something
我給各位講一件事情
think about it
你想想看
You now have two strategies
你現在有兩個策略
Let's assume you are cooperating with defender
我們去假設你這個人cooperate跟defender
Let's assume that the other party will cooperate with you
我們先假設對方會跟你合作
Then do you want to betray him?
那你要不要出賣他
Four points for betraying him, right?
要 出賣他的話會拿四分 對不對
Then what
然後呢
if the other party betrays you
如果對方要出賣你
more to betray him
更要出賣他
So why did I just say that there is one of the most interesting aspects of the game?
所以我剛為什麼講說賽局有一個最有趣的地方就是說
you have to be able to imagine what you want to do
你要能夠想像你自己要做什麼
to imagine what he would do
要想像他會做什麼
so feel weird
所以覺得怪怪的
i will betray him
我會出賣他
he will betray me
他一定會出賣我
right
對不對
so what is the end result
所以最後的結果是什麼
so how many points will you end up with
所以你最後會得到多少分
Is the result of 22 good?
二二的結果好不好
not good
不好
This is a very interesting example
這個是一個非常有趣的例子
I'm going to use this as an example for someone who hasn't learned the game at all
我會用這個例子來講那個完全沒有學過賽局的人
That said, the funniest part of the game is here
那說賽局最有趣的地方在這裡
22 He is the only one among the four results that does not belong to paradise optimal
二二他是這四個結果當中唯一一個不屬於paradise optimal的結果
What is paradise optimal
什麼叫paradise optimal
how to define
要怎麼界定
if a result can't be better
如果一個結果不能更好的話
The result is paradise optimal
這個結果就是paradise optimal
Then we now find that there are four results on the side of these four results
然後我們現在發現說這四個結果這邊有四個結果
The only result that is not paradise optimal is mutual betrayal
唯一不屬於paradise optimal的結果只有相互背叛
But he is the only balance
可是他是唯一的均衡
Do you know what I'm talking about?
大家知道我在講什麼嗎
That is to say if
就是說明明如果
If you cooperate with each other, you can get three points.
相互合作都可以拿到三分啊
But why do you betray each other by two points?
可是你為什麼要相互背叛兩分
so i'm thinking like this
所以我這樣在想說
If you have time, watch the first episode of Wu Jiandao
你們有空的話再去看那個吳堅道第一集
that was a difficult choice
那是很困難的抉擇
I just send a signal to the other party
就我送一個信號給對方
will he believe it
他會相信嗎
Even if he believes, will he be sentenced to me?
就算他相信他會不會被判我嗎
Because Wu Jian said that he actually talked about a
因為吳堅道他其實講了一個
It's human
是人性啦
But it's also one of the most troubling issues of game theory.
但是也是一個賽局理論最困擾的問題
How can I keep the other party from going out?
我要怎麼樣讓對方不會出門
Very difficult
很困難
Then this often happens
然後這種狀況經常出現
often appear in our life
在我們的生活當中經常出現
That is, if we both choose to trust each other
就是說如果我們都選擇相信對方
Maybe I will be betrayed by the other party
可能我會被對方出賣呢
So when I think about it I think it's still a bit new
所以我想一想我覺得還是很新一點
I just sold him
我乾脆把對方賣了
And at this time the police actually knew
而且這個時候警察他其實都知道
even if you call
你就算打電話給對方
The other party will still sell you
對方還是會把你賣掉
This has nothing to do with Information
這個跟Information一點關係都沒有
Let's say I got a call from you saying
比如說我接到你的電話說
i will cooperate with you
我會跟你合作
I'll send you a press number to say
我送一個按號給你說
let you see him betray him
讓你看他把他出賣
Then there must be a conspiracy
然後這裡一定是一個陰謀
remember me
要記我的意思嗎
Of course we say from a statistical point of view
當然啦 我們說從統計學的觀點來看
really do experiments
也真的去做實驗
Of course we know that it means that most of the opponent's battles will be betrayed.
我們當然知道就是說這裡面會去出賣對方的戰絕大多數
But there are still a few
但是還是有少數人
Few people he didn't choose to betray each other
少數人他沒有選擇出賣對方
Then this minority is worth studying.
那這個少數人是蠻值得研究
why didn't you betray the other side
你為什麼沒有去出賣對方
Of course one of the simplest answers is in the laboratory
當然一個最簡單的答案是在實驗室裡
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
Do an experiment, do an experiment in social science
做實驗啦 社會科學做實驗
The biggest problem is that he has no external effects
最大的困擾是他沒有外部效力
I'm in the lab and of course I can believe anything
我在實驗室裡我當然可以相信任何的事情
good
好
sitting sitting sitting
坐著坐著坐著
right
對
good
好
Yeah
對對對
somewhat related
有有點關係
Then I think it will be more betrayal
那我想比較會出賣
So it won't be like this two sessions
所以它不會這樣兩會這個賽局
this is the real game
這真的賽局
The game will take these factors you just won
賽局會把你剛扛勝的這些因素
all as unknowns
全部當作未知數
For example, I now assume
比如說我現在假設
For example, the judge and the defendant
比如說法官跟被告
he is playing a game
他在玩一場賽局
Then I would say that the judge's package matches the defendant's package
那我會說法官的配套跟被告的配套
He is, say, XYD or something
他是比如說叫做XYD之類的
Then I will say under what conditions
然後我會說在什麼樣的條件底下
The end result is that he'll plead guilty and negotiate.
最後的結果是他會認罪協商
This game is actually not that difficult
這個賽局其實沒有這麼困難
Why
為什麼
Because he must know the judge's attitude
因為他一定知道法官的態度
The two sides do not know each other's attitude
雙方不知道彼此的態度
That is, when a game is played
就是說一個賽局在玩的時候
it comes in various forms
它有各種的型態
message is very important
訊息是非常重要的一件事情
If I could somehow
如果我可以透過一些方法
let you know my attitude is this
讓你知道我的態度是這個
It's actually too simple
其實太簡單了
through a lawyer
那只要透過律師
can already let him know
就已經可以讓他知道
you just plead guilty
你只要認罪
you can come out
你就可以出來
Introspect, that's what it means
反省啦 就是這個意思
So this game is actually not that difficult
所以這個賽局其實沒有這麼困難
So I think
所以我覺得
want
要
right
對
meeting
會
i totally agree with you
我完全同意你的看法
that is
就是說
In this case if you
這個case 如果你
it shouldn't be what i want to talk about
應該不是我要講的事情
I don't study law
我不是學法律的
But I think from studying the law
但是我覺得從學法
have a point of view on this matter
就有觀點來看這件事情
it is legal
它是合法的
OK the main problem is plea bargaining
OK 主要的問題是認罪協商
there is something wrong with the system
這個制度有問題
Anyway
Anyway
simply speaking
簡單來講
When the judge made this decision
法官他做這個決定的時候
If he thinks it's legal
他如果覺得這是合法的
Will he care what voters are thinking
他會不會care選民在想什麼
Nope
不會啊
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
Because we usually judge
因為我們一般在審判的時候
It's all prosecutors who want to present
都是檢察官要present出來
I'm going to sue this guy
我要空告這個人
Then your proof is
然後你的證據是
prosecutors decision
檢察官決定
Judges can only rely on prosecutors
法官只能根據檢察官
Bring the evidence to trial
提出來的證據再做審判
so you want to do one thing
所以你要想一件事情
let's not talk about this case
我們不要講這個case
we talk
我們講說
Black heart food is ready
黑心食品好了
Why is black heart food innocent in the end?
黑心食品為什麼最後是無罪
Of course, many people reacted directly and scolded the judge.
那很多人當然直接反應去罵法官
but you need to know
可是你要知道
it's a sequential game
它是一個sequential的game
As a result, the judge finally has to make a verdict
結果法官最後要做一個判決
You must only look at the evidence presented by the prosecutor.
一定只能看檢察官提出來的證據
So many people feel
所以很多人會覺得
prosecutors are responsible
檢察官要負責
yes
是啊
But the prosecutor
可是檢察官
what are you responsible for
你要是要負什麼責任
because it is based on what
因為它是根據什麼
According to the real security law
根據實安法
Who made the real security law?
實安法是誰定的
your elected status
你們選出來的地位
the people themselves
是人民自己
What do you mean?
這個意思嗎
that is
就是說
It's a pretty complicated political issue
這是一個蠻複雜的政治問題
Then why did the legislators make a real case that is difficult to implement?
那立委為什麼要定出來一個很難執行的實案吧
OK, then you will say that the legislator came from there before the election
OK 那你就會說那立委選舉前從那一來
OK that's why I think
OK 所以我才覺得
I can't talk about this anymore
這個就不能再講下去了
That is to say, in fact, many times
那就是說其實很多時候
people have only themselves to blame
人民只能怪自己
For example, when you are in an election
比如說你在選舉的時候
How on earth did you unify that vote?
你到底怎麼統一那一票
But I think that's changing
但是我覺得那個正在改變
i think it's changing
我覺得正在改變
At least many people will be dissatisfied with this verdict
至少很多人會對這個判決不滿意
he should
他應該會
This Act of Act should be amended in the future
應該會將來要修這個實案法
because you know you have problems at the source
因為你知道你源頭出問題
There will be problems later on
後面通通都會出問題
OK so all I can do is
OK 所以我能夠做的就是
You have to take a good look at your actual case law
你要好好地看一下你實案法
What are you listening in?
裡面到底聽什麼
the law of fact
就是透過外面的實案法
if there is a judge
如果有一個法官
know that the court has a
知道法院有一個這樣的
is to be judged
是要審判的
yes
是啊
right
對
Now this heaven about this political situation
現在這個天堂關於這個政治的情況
I agree
我同意
many people like this
很多人這樣子
certainly
當然
you know the biggest problem right now is
你知道現在最大的問題是
Your current law will make the final judgment difference
你現在的法律會讓最後的判決差異
this is the biggest problem
這是最大的問題
Which means you're giving judges too much freedom to administer.
也就是說你給法官太多自由行政的權利
He can also follow this exactly
他可以同樣完全按照這個
say he is guilty
說他有罪
He can also say he is innocent
他也可以說他無罪
because many details
因為當中很多細節
but i think this is
但是我覺得這個是
yes
沒錯
So I think you still have to look at the content of the law at the source
所以我覺得源頭你還是要去看法律的內容
but i believe many people
但是我相信很多人
Most people haven't read the real security law
大多數人都沒有看過實安法
You're interested to see what exactly they stipulate
你有興趣去看看他們到底規定什麼
ok
好啦
Then we have to finish our topic
那我們必須要把我們話題講完
what to do
怎麼辦
Can everyone understand this?
這個大家可以了解嗎
This is a very, very simple game
這個就是一個非常非常簡單的賽局
It's very simple, just two people
就非常簡單只有兩個人
Two people
兩個人
Only two strategies per person
每個人只有兩個策略
I can't imagine an easier game
我不能想像一個賽局更簡單
Simultaneous action
同時行動
It turned out to be a tragedy indeed
結果確實是一場悲劇
that's why
这就是为什么
4 is better than 3 3 is better than 2 2 is better than 1
4比3好 3比2好 2比1好
It is your cooperation points, how much benefit you get
就是你的配合分你拿到多少好处
Because I want people to understand right away
因为我要让大家能够马上了解
Because this may for example
因为这个可能比如说
You can use the reverse operation how long you will be locked up
你可以用反向操作你会被关多久
Then I just temporarily use the order of the size
那我这边只是暂时把它的顺序用大小
so that everyone can understand
让大家可以了解
I'm just saying the rules of the game are simple
我就说这里面的游戏规则很简单
Everyone wants to get the highest score
每一个人都希望自己拿到最高的分数
But the final result was the penultimate time
可是拿到最后的结果是倒数第二次
Right
对吧
i sure wish i had better get out
我当然希望我最好赶快出去
But when everyone counts like this
可是当每一个人都这样计算的时候
would create a big problem
会产生一个很大的困扰
is when each of you counts like this
就是当你每一个人都这样算的时候
The end result is really unwanted
最后的结果是真的不想要的
but there is no way
可是没有办法
Then I would think that this is actually called
那我会觉得说其实这个叫
Later they became matchmakers
后来他们做赛局人
There's a reason it's called the Prisoner's Dilemma
把它叫囚犯难题有它的道理
You say that when we engage in social action
你就说我们在从事社会行动的时候
often in places where the prisoners are very ordinary
经常处在囚犯很平淡的地方
What kind of relationship do I want to maintain with the other party?
就是我到底要跟对方保持什么样的关系
Very difficult
很困難
Of course there are many people who are solving the criminal problem
當然有很多人在解求犯難題
The first one is you let him keep playing
第一個就是你讓他繼續玩下去
Will the second round be better?
第二回合會比較好呢
Won't
不會
really won't
真的不會
round three will be worse
第三回合會更糟
OK
OK
Because you have betrayed me before
因為你前面都已經出賣我了
now don't i betray you
現在難道我不要出賣你嗎
One way is you let him keep playing
那有一個方法是你讓他繼續玩下去
But don't know he knows when it will lift
但是不知道他知道什麼時候會解除
it's an interesting inference
這是很有趣的推論
because when you
因為當你
I say this by the way
我順便這樣講
That is to say, when you are in this state
就是說當你處在這個狀態當中
you have to keep playing with him
你要繼續跟他玩下去
But when you're not sure when it's gonna end
但是你不確定什麼時候會結束的時候
he's going to be a really interesting thing
他會變成一個非常有趣的東西
called culture
叫做文化
culture comes from here
文化是從這邊來的
what is culture
什麼叫做文化
Culture is a norm that everyone abides by
文化就是大家遵守的一個規範
And he's not legal
而且他不是法律規定的
That is to say when you talk to each other
就是說當你跟對方
when you've been in this kind of trouble
一直處在這種難題當中的時候
do you feel good
你會覺得好嗎
I believe you first
我先相信你
Do you want to believe me too
你要不要也相信我
When I found out that it was okay
發現說還可以的時候
Next round he will strengthen
下一回合他會增強
That is to say, you will find out whether to say betrayal or not to betray
就是說你會發現說背叛跟不背叛
It enhances the result of the previous round
它會增強前一回合的結果
So if some people happen to
所以如果剛好有一些人
They didn't think that much
他們其實沒有想那麼多
He said I just believe you
他說我就相信你了
then you also believe me
那你也相信我
I feel it's ok
我覺得還不錯
so it becomes a
所以它會變成一種
often called culture
經常講的叫做文化
very funny
很有趣
The starting point of that culture is actually the game
那文化的起點其實是賽局
Although we are talking about culture all day long
雖然我們現在一天到晚在講文化
But it's like not talking
可是等於沒有講
a thing we often talk about
我們經常講的一件事情
That is why it does such a bad thing
就是說它為什麼會做這種壞事
because it's a criminal
因為它是一個罪犯
why is this what he is talking about now
為什麼這個他現在講什麼
why is it a criminal
它為什麼是一個罪犯
because it does bad things
因為它做壞事
ok
好啦
So what I'm saying is
所以我講的意思就是說
The starting point of many problems is actually in this state
很多問題的起點其實處在這個狀態
yes
是
what's the problem
那什麼問題
It is to be the lower body of the relationship between the various bodies
就是要做各體關係的下身
yes
是
that this is official
那這個正式
Should be from formal relationship fairness to
應該是從正式關系公平到
They ended up with both being locked up
他們的結果就是兩個人都被關了
This is pushed from the individual to the collective
這是從個體推到集體
We start from a formal relationship
我們從正式的關系
and then implement something
然後去實施上什麼東西
this question is very good
這個問題非常好
Then I'll just tell you the following passage
那我就乾脆幫你講下面的這一段
Because you have asked the following question
因為你已經把下面的問題問出來
I really don't have enough time
我時間真的不太夠
I'll just jump
我就跳動一下好了
do you know who wrote this book
這本書知道是誰寫的嗎
Leviathan
Leviathan
yes
對啊
his name is already on it
他名字已經在上面了
is this person
是這個人
Thomas Hoss
Thomas Hoss
why did he write this book
他為什麼要寫這本書
We certainly can't say he invented the barter puzzle.
我們當然不能說求換難題是他發明的
no
不是
But his Revision
但是他的Revison
Theme of
的主題
The main argument is very similar to
主要的argument非常像的
Revision
Revison
If I may, I can briefly summarize it like this
我如果可以這樣稍微摘要一下
Though I'm not thinking of testifying
雖然我不是作證的思想
he has a very important concept
他有一個非常重要的概念
That is to say, through this book
就是說你透過這本書
You can see why sovereignty is necessary
你可以知道為什麼主權是必要的
Sovereignty is otherwise necessary
主權稍不然是必要的
why what is sovereignty
為什麼 什麼叫主權
because
因為
Hobbes he would describe a state of nature
霍布斯他會描繪一個自然狀態
what is the state of nature
什麼叫自然狀態
just two swaps
就是兩個求換
right
對不對
Then your two begging
那你的兩個求換
You can
你會
see the state of nature
見一下自然狀態
is what they will do
就是他們會做什麼事情
He used a metaphor, which I think is very expressive.
他用了一個比喻 我覺得非常的傳神
Which means they all have swords in their hands.
就是說他們手上都拿到刀劍
sword in hand
手上都拿到刀劍
He'll kill you when he gets a chance
他找機會就把你幹掉
So the final result is
所以最後產生的結果是
we just saw the previous one
我們剛剛看到前面那個
that neutral defect
那個neutral defection
betray each other
相互背叛
So they are in a state
所以他們處在一種狀態
it's a very bad state
就是一種非常糟糕的狀態
as a result of you protecting yourself
因為你保護自己的結果
make you mistrust each other
卻讓你們相互不信任對方
right
對不對
So better results
所以比較好的結果
Let's take a look at the previous one
我們看一下剛剛前面那一張
better result
比較好的結果
It should be changed from two two to three three, right?
應該是從二二變了三三對不對
who can do such a thing
那誰能夠做這樣的事情
So Hobbes he established his theory
所以霍卜斯他就建立了他的理論
That is to say, who can
就是說誰能夠在
Under the situation where everyone is against everyone
人人跟人人為敵的狀況底下
This is the prisoner's problem
這個就是囚犯難題
can cooperate with each other
可以相互合作
He said there is only one power
他說只有一種力量
called advice
叫做advice
distance
距離
This is the concept of sovereignty
這個就是所謂主權的概念
Then we from this point of view
那我們從這個觀點
you can see this
就可以看到這個
From this point of view, we can compare
那我們從這個觀點就可以比
you only need to know hobbes
你只要了解霍布斯
why is he so annoying
他為什麼這麼對人討厭
But why are you here today
可是為什麼大家到今天
still studying him
還一直在研究他
because he told us one thing
因為他告訴我們一件事情
politics is inevitable
政治是不可避免的
i just wanted to say
我只是想想說
i should hire an economist
我應該請經濟學家
Study the Prisoner's Problem
研究一下囚犯難題
how will they feel
他們會有什麼感覺
that feeling might be
那感覺可能是
that is a special case
那是一個特例
That's a special case
那是一個特例啊
Really
真的嗎
because i just
因為我剛剛
Such logic is completely consistent with
這樣的邏輯完全是符合
the rational logic used by economists
經濟學家用的那個理性邏輯
but then why did you say
可是那你為什麼說
Rational logic is a special case
理性邏輯是特例
So Hobbes already saw
所以霍布斯早就已經看到
this problem
這個問題
He said that if there is no coercive person to come out
他說如果沒有一個強制的人出來
you on the handle
把手上的你
Swords in everyone's hands
大家手上的刀劍
when everything ends
通通收尾己有的時候
you'll keep going
你會繼續幹下去
That society is in a
那那個社會就處在一種
state of war
相互戰爭的狀態
So who can make
所以誰能夠讓
Swords in everyone's hands
大家手上的刀劍
wrap it up
把它收尾己有
only one thing called country
只有一個東西叫做國家
so now everyone knows
所以現在大家知道了嗎
what is the definition of country
國家的定義是什麼
Here we are
我們到了
There are many definitions of country
國家的定義有很多種
What do you think the definition of a country is?
不如你覺得國家的定義是什麼
Research is a thesis
考說是論文
Yes, you said nothing wrong
是啊 你講 沒有錯
What is a country? What is Weber's definition?
國家是什麼 韋伯的定義是什麼
I just know the definition of country now
我就 我現在知道國家的定義
Of course many kinds
當然很多種
That Max Weber from Germany
那Max Weber 德國的
Complicated. It's hard to say what subject he is in.
複雜他到底是什麼學科的很難講
He said that the state is actually a partner of legal violence
他說國家其實就是合法的暴力的同段者
Right, there should be nothing wrong with that, right?
對吧 這應該沒有錯吧
He is a
他是一個
Let him use force after legalization
經過合法以後讓他可以使用武力
Then come a system that restricts people's freedom
然後來拘束人民自由的一個體系
called national state stop
叫做國家 state stop
Then you know it's a very paradoxical definition
那你就知道這是一個非常吊詭的定義
On the one hand, he can concentrate everyone's weapons in his hands
一方面他可以把大家的武器集中到他手上
much like the army
很像軍隊
army or police
軍隊或者是警察
i can't imagine the army without guns
我沒有辦法想像軍隊沒有槍
You can't imagine the police without guns
你沒有辦法想像警察沒有槍
must be essentially a violence to them
對他們一定本質上是一種violence
But he is a legal violence
可是呢 他卻是一種合法的violence
Then this thing can help us answer
那這個東西剛好可以幫我們回答
Judgment problem its a solution
求判難題它的一種解決方式
As far as HOPPS it tells us that
就HOPPS它告訴我們說
When everyone and everyone are in a state of mutual hostility
當每個人跟每個人都處在相互敵對的狀態當中的時候
And even if you want to cooperate with the other party
而且就算你要跟對方合作
when it ignores you
它不會理你的時候
only one way
只有一種方法
is you let a sovereign come out
就是你讓一個sovereign出來
Take all the knives in everyone's hands
把大家手上的刀 通通收過來
Then say you don't fight now
然後說現在你們都不要打了
because i can kill you both
因為我可以把你們兩個都幹掉
So the state it is violent in nature
所以國家它本質上是暴力的
But its violence is with the consent of the people
但是它的暴力是經過人民同意的
It's a hanging rail, isn't it?
這是一個吊軌對不對
I make you agree
我讓你同意
I can take the sword from your hand
我可以把你的手上的刀劍拿過來
no way
那沒辦法
We have to see the result
我們只好看到這樣的結果
Then let me ask you one thing by the way
那我順便問大家一件事情
Do you know when the revision was written?
大家知道那個revising什麼時候寫的嗎
when was distance soul written
距離靈魂是什麼時候寫的
guess and guess
猜又猜的
16 then 17
16 然後17
Okay, okay, he should have published several versions of the performance he published.
好了好了 這個他出版的演他應該出了好幾個版本
1651 what happened in 1651
1651年 1651年發生什麼事情
A very important event happened in 1651
1651年發生一件非常重要的事情
1651 English Civil War ended
1651年英國的內戰結束了
That Britain itself had a civil war that lasted for decades.
那個英國本身有內戰 長達幾十年的時間
There were a lot of little battles, and later everyone called that period
有很多小的戰役 後來大家把那段時間叫做
Cyber War
Cyber War
So he was in a state where the war was over and he was writing this
所以他是處在一個戰爭結束的狀態底下 他寫這個東西
So he has very, very strong space-time
所以他有非常非常強的時空性
He told you that we went through the Civil War in England
他告訴你說我們經過英國的內戰
We did see that the British people really wanted to kill each other
我們的確看到英國人民真的是要殺害彼此
And you can't say that the other party is malicious, no
而且你不能說對方有惡意 沒有
So your only recourse is to stop calling
所以你唯一的方法就是不要再打了
stop calling so
不要再打了 所以
And let's not forget what happened in 1651
而且大家不要忘記 1651年是什麼事情
It is the three years since the concept of the so-called Modern State came out.
就是所謂的Modern State 這個概念出來以後的三年
I think these historical cases
我覺得這些歷史的案例
Actually it has its connection
其實它有它的連結性
has its connectivity
有它的連結性
And don't forget
而且大家不要忘記了
what happened in 1649
1649年發生什麼事情
In 1649 England did a crazy thing
1649年英國做一件crazy的事情
They wrapped Chelster First around their heads
他們把Chelster First 纏首
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
Are you not interested in British history?
你們對英國歷史沒有興趣嗎
Don't know where the UK is?
不知道英國在哪裡嗎
Should I have heard Chelster First?
Chelster First 應該聽過嗎
when he wrote that book
就他寫那本書的時候
The UK happens to be in Common Wales
英國剛好在Common Wales
The one in Cromwell
就是在Cromwell的那個
Columbware
Columbware
UK's Chelster First has been headbanded
英國的Chelster First 已經被纏首了
Why is it tied up
為什麼會被纏首
because everyone voted
因為大家投票通過
So when Chelster First is going to be tied up
所以Chelster First 要被纏首的時候
also gave a speech
還發表一場演講
he said no way
他說沒辦法
this is what everyone means
這是大家的意思
It's interesting
這很有趣
Because it's mostly parliament that's against the king
因為主要是國會在反對國王
OK mostly congress is against the king
OK 主要是國會在反對國王
So everyone thinks it should be wrapped around the head
所以大家覺得應該要把它纏首
From a symbolic point of view
從象徵的角度來看
If he could put a king to death
他如果能夠把一個國王處於死刑
Congress is very powerful
代表國會的力量非常大
So actually we
所以其實我們
When he returned to history
他還原到歷史的時候
we probably know one thing
我們大概知道一件事情
If we look at British history
我們如果看英國的歷史
That is to say, Congress is very powerful.
就是說國會的力量很大
then he can decide the king
然後他可以決定國王
to be beheaded
要被斬首
then you say
然後你說
Huh? What about Chelst II?
欸?Chelst II呢
Where
在哪裡
Just his son
就他兒子啊
Yes, his son's name is Chelst II
有啊,他兒子叫Chelst II
just said
就是剛剛講
Let that John Grant
讓那個John Grant
The one that can go to the British Academy
可以去英國學會的那個
where is he
他在哪裡
he said where was he
他說他在哪裡
so
這樣
he must exist somewhere, right?
他一定存在在某個地方對不對
yes he is in france
是,他在法國
I think European royal families are very interesting
我覺得歐洲的王室非常的有趣
they usually occur in a country
他們通常在一個國家發生
In times of trouble he fled to France
問題的時候他逃到法國去
because they are relatives
因為他們彼此都是親戚
so he's in france
所以他處在法國
Then of course
那後來當然
Something very important happened in England
英國發生了一件非常重要的事情
It should be 1689
應該是1689年
That's called the Glorious Revolution
那個叫做光榮革命
What is the Glorious Revolution
什麼叫光榮革命
You see these things are connected
你看這些事情就連起來
that is
就是說
when we feel a normal
當我們覺得一個正常的
When the government should be legal to have the tools of violence
政府應該是合法的擁有暴力的工具的時候
The composition of your government itself is very important
你這個政府本身的組成是很重要的事情
You want to make the government itself unable to use its violence
你要讓這個政府本身不能去用它的暴力
Hence the concept of legalization
所以才有合法化這個概念
So I think the core issue of political science is
所以我就覺得說政治學最核心的問題就是
A government cannot be free from violence
一個政府不可能沒有暴力
The second is do you want to use this violence
第二個是你要用這個暴力嗎
OK these are two things but related
OK這是兩件事情但是是相關
So I think we're probably seeing
所以我覺得我們現在大概看到了
He MustHops he's in this historical situation
他MustHops他處在這個歷史的狀況當中
we still have a little time
那我們還有一點點的時間
Then how do we study that authority
那我們要怎麼樣去研究那個authority
I'll just talk about it
我就講這個問題好了
So I do a little bit of a simple summary
所以我稍微做一些簡單的摘要
That means game theory, he studies war.
就是說賽局理論他研究戰爭
In fact, his essence is to study war
其實他本質是研究戰爭
Research Dominance
研究Dominance
Then statistics he is hoping
然後統計學他是希望
What's up
有事嗎
Statistics He hopes to learn the most things with the least cost
統計學他是希望用最小的成本了解最多的事情
Then political science is the study of conflicts between people
然後政治學本來就是在研究人跟人的衝突
So the core issues of these three things are very close
所以這三件事情的核心議題很接近
But the method used is different
但是用的方法是不一樣
That just means that after the establishment of the modern state
那只是說在現代國家建立了以後
Gradually the disciplines are separated
慢慢慢慢學科就分開了
i can't imagine saying
我沒有辦法想像說
will ground it at that time
將ground它在那個時候
what kind of scientist is it
它是哪一種學家
Its real identity is the person in the sales department
它真正的身份是賣部的人
ok you say Thomas Hopes
ok 你說Thomas Hopes
what is it
它是什麼學家
it is everything
它什麼都是
nothing
什麼都不是
but that is in the modern country
但是那個是在現代國家
when not yet established
還沒有建立的時候
So after the establishment of the modern state
所以現代國家建立了以後
There are so-called disciplines
才有所謂的學科
That's why we are so poor today
才有我們今天很可憐的
I'm still writing when I get home
我回家還在寫配的
That means I must contribute
就是說我一定要投稿
Political Semester Opens
政治學期開
Otherwise, it would not be regarded as
要不然就沒有被人家當作
One of the best virtuous people of this generation
這個世代最好的一個唯德人
Kidding
開玩笑的
i mean
我意思就是說
this is our tragedy
這是我們的悲劇
But what I'm going to say is
但是我要講的事情就是說
this thing will make us
這個事情會讓我們
really have to reflect on one thing
真的要反省一件事情
Then we can now use
那我們現在可以用
what we just talked about
我們剛剛講的這些東西
Are you here to study political science?
來研究政治學嗎
Can
可以
ok, since we talk about political science and
ok 既然講說政治學跟
game theory and statistics
賽局理論跟統計學
If there is such a close relationship
有這麼密切的關係的話
let's see
我們就來看看
what kind of things it can do
它可以做什麼樣的事情
As an example
舉一個例子
Let's take this example
我們就舉一個這個例子
Devexche's Law
Devexche's Law
Mohist Devexche the French scholar
Mohist Devexche這個法國的學者
he has a very simple definition
他有一個非常簡單的定義
He said the electoral system affects the party system
他說選舉制度會影響政黨體系
Don't forget that he said this in the 1950s
大家不要忘記了他講這句話的時候是1950年代
1950s
1950年代
We now feel that it is a very common sense thing
我們現在覺得那是很common sense的事情
but he said
可是他講說
If there is a constituency, he will only elect a winner
如果一個選區他只會選出一個winner
Just like Taiwan's single constituency system
就像現在台灣的單一選區制
A single constituency in the two-vote system
兩票制當中的單一選區
When there is only one winner
只有一個winner的時候
votes for each of your constituencies
你每一個選區的選票
will focus on the top two candidates
會集中在前兩個候選人身上
It's called the M plus E rule.
就叫做M加E法則
M is District Magnitude
M就是District Magnitude
what did he say
他說呢
If your current system is proportional representation
如果你現在用的制度是比例代表制
It depends on how many places you have in the British election.
那看你的英選名額有多少
Proportional representation is good for multiparty
比例代表制是有利於多黨制
Of course, there is another system that was used in France at that time.
當然還有一種制度是法國當時用的制度
Called two rounds of voting Round out
叫兩輪投票Round out
he said two rounds of voting were fun
他說兩輪投票很有趣
The effect on the party system of two rounds of voting is
兩輪投票的對政黨體系的影響是
it won't be bipartisan
也不會是兩黨制
It won't be a true multiparty system either.
也不會是真正的多黨制
He wants more than both parties
他要比兩黨再多一點
Why
為什麼
have you ever thought about this
有沒有想過這個問題
why don't i ask you again
不如我不要再問你了
ok
好啦
you go back to his core proposition
你就回到他的核心命題
His core proposition is a game problem
他的核心命題就是一個賽局的問題
if we feel
如果我們覺得
The core problem of an electoral system is
一個選舉制度最核心的問題是
How many people can be elected in a constituency
一個選區有幾個人可以當選
right
對不對
we'll actually talk now
我們現在實際上會講說
Taiwan's electoral system is very unfair to small parties
台灣這個選舉制度對小黨很不公平是
because of your constituency
因為你選區
There is not only one seat in the British election
英選沒有只有一席
So M is equal to 1
所以M等於1
then you get a corollary
那你就會得到一個推論
When M is equal to 1
那M等於1的時候
Voters' votes will be concentrated in M ​​plus 1 is two
選民的投票會集中在M加1就是兩個
above the political party
政黨上面
Well, there's some interesting mathematical corollary here.
那這裡面有一些蠻有趣的數學推論
This inference is actually part of the game
這個推論其實是賽局的部分
why don't i give my vote to the third candidate
我為什麼不要把選票給第三個候選
he will not go up
他一定不會上
correct
沒有錯
then you have to figure it out
那你要把它算出來
why won't he come
他為什麼不會上
ok
ok
So he said it himself
所以他自己這樣講
When he taught this theory in the 1950s
他在1950年代講這個理論的時候
He said
他說
Of course he didn't learn the game himself.
他當然本身沒有學賽局
But he talked about two effects
但是他講了兩個effect
One is the mechanical effect
一個就是mechanical effect
Another psychological effect
另外一個psychological effect
mechanical effect
mechanical effect
Effect means different electoral systems
Effect就是說不同的選舉制度
it will have different thresholds
它會有不同的門檻
M size is subject to change
M大小是有變動的
He said your last party number
他說你最後的政黨的數目
number of valid candidates in other regions
它地區性的有效候選人數
will be related to M
會跟M有關係
The second voter also looks at the so-called Mocanical Effect
第二個選民也會看所謂的Mocanical Effect
If voters say that the M in this constituency is too low
選民如果說這個選區這個M太低了
He said I don't want to waste my vote
他說我不要浪費我的選票
Everyone now knows what it means to waste your vote
大家現在知道什麼叫浪費你的選票
as soon as we hear
我們一聽到在講
7x keep Y right?
7x保Y對不對
That's what I mean
就是這個意思
That's called strategic voting
那個叫策略投票
Everyone is very familiar with this
這個大家都非常的熟悉
On January 16, you will know what strategic voting is
1月16號你就知道什麼叫策略投票
And I know our strategic vote now
而且我知道我們現在的策略投票
very very complicated
非常非常的複雜
I still haven't figured out how to vote myself
我自己都還沒搞清楚要怎麼投票
anyway
anyway
This thing affects everyone's life
這個東西影響每一個人的生活
But he talked about it in the 1950s
可是他在1950年代就講了這件事情
Then what we're going to ask now is
然後我們現在要問的是
This is a very, very famous definition in political science
這是一個政治學當中非常非常有名的定義
Can he be studied?
他可不可以被研究可以
Of course, when he brought up such a thing in the 1950s
當然他在1950年代提了這樣的一個東西出來的時候
you can't see any equation
你看不到任何一個equation
he said it
他是用說的
I will say one thing by the way
我順便講一件事情
that newton he wrote that
那個牛頓他寫那個
GBRVC is the original time of physics
GBRVC就是物理學原本的時候
He also didn't use Equation
他也沒有用Equation
ok
好啦
you should read that book
這個你應該去看一下那本書
That is, he just uses Hirao straight numbers like this
就是他就是用平夫直數這樣子
But there are many, many, many people behind him
可是他後面有非常非常非常多的人
testing his theory
在驗證他的理論
This is Divac shape
這個就是Divac shape
OK this is him
OK 這個是他
that's st paul's church
那是聖保羅教堂
It was a symbol of authority at the time
那是當時的權威的象徵
I don't know why he took this photo
我不知道他為什麼拍這張相片
That is, he is higher than that authority
就是他比那個權威還要高
should have that meaning
應該就有這個意思
this is the expiration of the camera
這是相機的期滿
ok
好啦
One of our most interesting questions is
我們一個最有趣的問題是
Do you think the law of Divac shape is Low
你覺得Divac shape的法則Low
Is it a Low?
是一個Low嗎
Because we usually talk about the laws of science
因為我們平常講科學的定律
We usually use the word Low
我們通常會用Low這個字
it is a law
它是一個定律
But do you think its Low is Low?
可是你覺得它的Low是Low嗎
this is an interesting question
這是一個很有趣的問題
then let me tell a little story
那我先講一個小故事
That is to say, this Divac shape itself
就是說這個Divac shape它本人
he did not study political science
他沒有學過政治學
he never studied political science
他從來沒有學過政治學
Then what do you say he studied?
那你說他學什麼
He studies law
他學法律
just call it lol
就叫LOL
just kidding
就開玩笑
do you know i'm kidding
知道我在開玩笑嗎
this is no joke
這不是開玩笑
it's true
這真的啦
he has a
他有一個
The one he just mentioned
他剛剛前面講的那個
How electoral systems affect party systems
選舉制度如何影響政黨體系
He said it's called LOL
他說這個叫做LOL
Although he himself is a LOL
雖然他本身是一個LOL
well
好好
scholars
的學者
but
但是呢
he made a very important contribution
他有一個很重要的貢獻
He after World War II
他在二次大戰以後
He founded the Department of Politics in France
他在法國創立了政治系
Formerly French Faculty of Politics
以前法國的政治系
In fact, it is part of LOL
其實就是屬於LOL的一部分
because he tells you how to rule
因為他告訴你怎麼統治
In fact, some countries still
其實現在有一些國家還是一樣
that is
就是說
In fact, political science is very close to law.
其實政治學跟法學非常的接近
As far as political science is actually the law department
就政治學其實就是法學部
or law school
或者法學院
a branch at the bottom
底下的一個分支
But what we talk about political science now is not
但是我們現在講政治學不是
So he created himself
所以他本身就創立了
so-called political science in french
所謂法國的政治科學
then of course we later
然後我們當然後來
After he dropped such a thing and came out
他丟了這樣的一個東西出來以後
Many people helped him correct
很多人就幫他修正
This fix is ​​itself a Test
這個修正本身就是一個Test
The first one hides some so-called game models in it
第一個它裡面隱藏了一些所謂的賽局的模型
For example, why should I vote strategically?
比如說我為什麼要策略投票
If the political party knows that voters will vote strategically
那政黨如果知道選民會策略投票
how is it nominated right
它怎麼提名對不對
This is an interactive process
這是一個互動的過程喔
if i knew you would piss me off
我如果知道你會把我氣掉的話
do i still nominate
我還要提名嗎
Or is my nomination bogus?
還是說我的提名是假的
do you know what i mean
了解我意思嗎
I really want you to vote for someone else
我真的要希望你投的是別人
OK, especially the two-vote system for a single constituency
OK 特別是單一選區兩票制
very complicated
非常的複雜
I may propose a false one in one constituency
我可能一個選區提假的
but i need your vote
可是我需要你的選票
vote for another party
投另外一個政黨票
We are now filled with such calculations
我們現在充滿了這種計算
So funny
太有趣了
We are counting and he is counting
我們也在計算他也在算
Well, many people helped him calculate this later.
好 那後來很多人幫他在算這個東西
Let his theory begin to formalize
就讓他的理論開始formalize
start more like a game
開始比較像一個賽局
And then a statistician comes in too
然後也有統計學家進來
what to do
做什麼事情
To see if his theory is true or not
要看他的理論到底是真還假的
Yes, because his theory is very simple
對 因為他的理論非常簡單
Your electoral system affects your party system
你的選舉制度會影響到你的政黨體系
Let's take a look at a data I saw
我們就來看一下我看到的一個data
this
這個
He means first pass the polls
他的意思就是first pass the polls
It's the British system
就是英國的制度
British and American systems
英國跟美國的制度
That is to say, the constituencies are the same across the country.
就是說全國的選區都一樣
first pass the polls
first pass the polls
Whoever gets the most votes is elected
就是誰的選票最多誰就當選
Elected with the highest number of votes
最高票當選
Then the two round system of TIS below
然後下面那個TIS的two round system
vote for two
就兩人投票
that france only recently voted
那個法國最近才進行過一次投票
two votes
兩人投票
Right-wing voices on the ground
就地方看起來右派的聲音
The far right speaks loudly
極右派的聲音很大
So it's Olon of the Socialist Party
所以變成是社會黨的Olon
He's going to speak to his former political enemy Sacozi
他要去跟他以前的政敵Sacozi講說
I still let you go
還是讓你上好了
Otherwise, it will be very troublesome if the extreme right is elected.
要不然極右派選上的話會很麻煩
Because he is in many areas with strong votes of the Socialist Party
因為他在很多社會黨的鐵票區
They're all extreme rightists
竟然都是極右派的人
Relatively speaking, the highest vote
相對來講最高票
So he had to let the political party do the mobilization
所以他只好由政黨去做動員說
Sacozi please come out
Sacozi拜託你出來
do you know
你知道嗎
This is the mobilization of a political party
這個就是一個政黨的動員
A 2 round system
一個2 round system
The last one is of course PR
最後一個當然就是PR
Proportional representation
Proportional representation
we see a very interesting thing now
我們現在看到一個很有趣的事情
Here is our observation paper
這邊是我們的觀察紙
This is the result of a sampling
這是一個抽樣的結果
then fate and obsession
然後有命跟迷戀
fate is different from infatuation
命跟迷戀不一樣
The word of fate is all the papers add up
命的話是所有的紙加起來
out of your observation
出於你的觀察
Midian is where you arrange
Midian就是你把排列
like row from smallest to largest
像從最小的排到最大的
then take the middle one
然後取中間那個
Then effectively shift
然後有效正檔
Effective positive file number it is actually an proxy
有效正檔數它事實上是一個approxy
The algorithm for the number of effective positive gears is
有效正檔數的算法就是
You take the square of the seat rate of each positive file
你把每一個正檔的席次率的平方
Add it up and remove it with E
加起來用E去除它
a little complicated
有點複雜
Just use E to divide a Sigma
就用E去除一個Sigma
Then the right side of Sigma
然後Sigma的右邊
It is the percentage of votes received by each positive file
就是每一個正檔的得票率
Sorry, the square of the seat rate
抱歉 席次率的平方
OK will get a number
OK 會得到一個數字
effective positive gear number
叫做有效正檔數
Etecific number of parties
Etecific number of parties
that's fun
那很有趣
We're looking at Midian
我們要看的是Midian
Then I was shocked when I saw the result
然後我看到這個結果也嚇了一跳
At least the training is right
至少地培訓是對的
as it was in the 1950s
因為它是在1950年代
writing this
在寫這個東西
But from my later data
可是我從後來的資料
This 2011 data
這2011年的資料
How much Midian is two
Midian多少 就是二
That is to say, what am I doing here?
也就是說我這邊做的事情是什麼
I know it has a theoretical expectation
我知道它有一個理論的預期
Theoretical expectations from games
從賽局來的理論的預期
說first pass to the post
說first pass to the post
it should form two gears
它應該會形成兩檔之的
I'm coming to check it out
我就正在來檢測一下
Then this test
然後這個檢測
Of course, many countries are not in between
當然很多國家不是兩檔之
some countries
有些國家
Some countries have few political parties
有些國家政黨數目很少
some a lot
有些很多
But its mystery is two
可是它的迷點就是二
so we know
所以我們知道
DVX he did a thing
DVX他做了一件事情
He uses a very simple pattern
他用一個很簡單的模式
tell us one thing
告訴我們一件事情
Then this thing can be verified
然後這件事情是可以被檢證的
I will testify for him now
我現在替他檢證
I see it like this
我看到就是這樣子
Let's look at PR again
我們再來看PR
the bottom one
最底下那個
Propulsion Rune Sensation 3.46
Propulsion Rune Sensation 3.46
What is the value
的確是多長值
some countries may have many
有些國家可能很多
Some countries have a high number of medical places
有些國家的醫學名額很高
relatively low
比較低
But he will not be two long values
但是他都不會是兩長值
very interesting
很有趣的是
TRS
TRS
Why 2.24
為什麼是2.24
Everyone never thought about this kind of problem
大家沒想過這種問題
that's a simple reason
那很簡單的道理
The so-called Turon System means
所謂的Turon System的意思是
two rounds of voting
兩輪投票
two rounds of voting means
兩輪投票的意思是
let's see the first round
我們先看第一輪
Is there anyone more than half
有沒有人過半
If there are more than half of the people, he will be elected
有人過半他就當選
but usually
可是通常呢
under this selection
在這種選字底下
You're gonna hope there's no one in the first round
你會希望第一輪沒有人過半
Right
對吧
so you just
所以你就
There will be a bunch of parties in the first round
第一輪會有一堆的政黨進來
Then see who's in the top two in the first round
然後比看誰在第一輪前兩名
do the second round
再進行第二輪
what would you do if you were young
如果你是小長你會做什麼事情
If you are a small party, now if Taiwan changes to
如果你是小黨現在如果台灣改成
From single constituency to two-vote system
從單一選區兩票制改成
For example, a two-round voting system
比如說兩輪投票制
what will you do
小黨你會做什麼事情
Of course you will threaten the big party
你當然會威脅大黨
So let's look at one thing now
所以我們現在看一件事情
first round of voting
第一輪投票
OK is comparing who is the top two
OK在比誰是前兩名
into the second round, right?
進第二輪對不對
So his competition is two
所以他的競爭的名額是二
So his effective party count will be more than two
所以他的有效政黨數會多於二
That's it
就是這樣
do you mean to me
你要對我的意思嗎
That is because of your two rounds of voting
就是說因為你兩輪投票
so that small parties have a chance
所以使得小黨有機會
Although he does not have majority support
他雖然沒有多數的支持
But he has a chance to advance to the second round
可是他可以有機會進到第二輪
so he can maintain a certain
所以他可以維持某一種
The existence of small parties
小黨存在的狀況
But the small party will not be too many
但是小黨不會太多
And two rounds of voting have one
而且兩輪投票有一個
very interesting effect
非常有趣的效應
He will make it necessary for political parties to cooperate
他會讓政黨之間必須要合作
Why
為什麼
because it's simple
因為很簡單
because you don't cooperate
因為你不合作
you will lose the second round
你第二輪一定輸
So the French think they
所以法國人他們覺得
their nationality is strange
他們的民族性很奇怪
not surprising
一點不奇怪
because you use two rounds of voting
因為你們用兩輪投票
french say
法國人說
Hate each other but I love him so much
恨對方可是我好愛他
it's not surprising
這一點都不奇怪
right
對不對
I said that's how you vote
我說你們選舉就這樣選的啦
i hate you now hate the key
我現在恨你恨的鑰匙
but two weeks later
可是兩個禮拜以後
we both made it to the second round
我們都進到第二輪
I have to cooperate with you
我只好跟你合作
That's it
就是這樣
Well, the good thing is that no one stays here.
那這個好在這邊沒有人留法
really not
真的沒有嗎
ok
好啦
That is to say, the electoral system
就是說這個選舉制度
will depend on your culture
會跟你的文化有關
But which one affects which
但是哪一個影響哪一個
that is
那個是
issues we can't discuss right now
我們現在沒有辦法討論的問題
good
好
So this is a very simple definition
所以這個就是一個很簡單的定義
that is
就是說
our 1950s
我們1950年代
someone throws this thing
有人就丟出這個東西來
Then the mechanism behind
然後後面的mechanism
yes
是
Actually
其實是
median voter
median voter
extension of
的延伸
That is to say, we can derive a law of M plus E
就是說我們可以得出一個M加E的法則
Then the key involved here
然後這裡面牽涉到的關鍵
Voters will vote strategically
就是選民會策略投票
Political parties will also strategically nominate
政黨也會策略的提名
Then he had a very clear prediction
然後他有非常清楚的預測
He said that if it was a unitary electoral system
他說如果是單一選舉制的話
will form a two-party system
會形成兩黨制
Sorry if it's the deputy director election
如果是副處選舉抱歉
In the case of proportional representation
如果是比例代表制的話
multi-party system
會形成多黨制
Then what
然後呢
DIS will be one of the two
DIS會介於兩者一件
It's about 2 o'clock
大概是2點多
what we see now is
我們現在看到是
It is right
它是正確的
So this is a good example
所以這個就是一個很好的例子
I'll go back
我就回到
the problem i started with
我一開始講的那個難題
What the hell is political science doing?
就政治學到底在做什麼事情
we probably know one thing now
我們現在大概知道一件事情
That is to say, political science is actually different from what everyone thinks now.
就是說政治學其實跟現在大家覺得
It seems to have nothing to do with politics
好像跟政治學一點關係都沒有的東西
actually its source
其實是它的源頭
next time maybe you can tell your friends
下次也許你可以跟你的朋友這樣講
statistics from political science
統計學從政治學來
He said you were crazy
他說你神經病
I tell you why it's called statistics
我告訴你為什麼它叫statistics
what does that mean
那什麼意思
you don't know right
你不知道對不對
To tell you statistics is to measure your country
告訴你statistics就是測量你的國家
I hope someone from the statistics office will come today
我希望今天有沒有統計所的人來
yes
對啊
I don't know if you talked about the origin of the word
我不知道你有沒有講這個字的起源
But that is a very real problem
但是那個是很現實的問題
The second question is to say
第二個問題就是說
does it have anything to do with the game
它跟賽局有沒有關係
of course
當然有
Because it's part of the nature of politics that I want to win
因為政治學的本質之一就是我要贏
do you know what i mean
了解我意思嗎
What do you hear most often now?
現在大家最常聽到的是什麼
who will win
誰會贏
Right
對吧
then how do i know i will win
然後我怎麼知道我會贏
I see polls
我看民調
Who will win is the question of the game
誰會贏是賽局的問題
polls are statistics
民調是統計學
Of course we know that the so-called polls
我們當然知道就是說所謂的民調
The current polls show that most of them are electric houses
現在的民調看到大部分都是電房
not very accurate
不是非常的準確
We certainly have some people who do very clear polls
我們當然有一些人做非常清楚的民調
He can't see it in the media
他媒體上看不出來
But I think basically Taiwan's polls
但是我覺得基本上台灣的民調
has his credibility
有他的可信度
So here we know one thing
所以這邊我們就知道一件事情
It is said that political science is a very old science
說政治學它本來就是一個很古老的科學
It is closely related to the establishment of the modern state
它跟現代國家的建立是有密切的關係
So we know that like statistical games
所以我們知道說像統計學的賽局
had a close relationship with it
本來都跟它有很密切的關係
OK, let's make another simple conclusion.
好 那我們再做一個簡單的結論
Sorry
Sorry
then turn around
那回過頭來
What questions do you think of when you look at our education system in Taiwan?
看我們台灣的教育體制你會想到什麼問題
my first question is
我第一個問題就說
they will ask me this question
他們會所問我這個問題
politics is not science
政治學不是科學
I also thought about this question for a long time
我也想這問題想了很久
In fact, it's useless for me to tell my mother.
其實我跟我媽講也沒有用
Because she still doesn't know what statistics are
因為她還不懂什麼叫統計
She still doesn't know which word statistics is
她還不知道統計是哪一個字
But I think a lot of people have this idea
但是我覺得很多人有這個想法
then i think we can imagine
那我覺得我們可以想像
If in the US or Europe
如果在美國或者是歐洲
Japan I don't know
日本我不知道
This problem should not be that serious
這個問題應該沒有那麼嚴重
for example
比如說
I don't know how American high school students choose courses
我不知道美國的高中生怎麼選課
But they should not be grouped
但是他們應該沒有分組
Then I don't know why Taiwan has to be grouped
那我不知道台灣為什麼一定要分組
Then the last math is a group
然後最後數學好的是一組
Mathematics is not good is another group
數學不好是另外一組
that's terrible
那多可怕
In fact I know a lot of people who read
事實上我知道很多人念
The so-called leaving the mouth is very painful
所謂的離嘴是很痛苦
They obviously like reading literature
他們明明就喜歡念文學
So you say literature should not study mathematics?
那你說文學不應該學數學嗎
wrong
錯啊
math is important
數學很重要
math is great
數學是很棒的事啊
don't know what i'm talking about
不知道我在講什麼
that is
就是說
We group students like this
我們把學生這樣分組
Actually it's not good
其實是不太好
because there are some problems
因為有一些問題
In fact, it is not a problem of the subject itself.
其實不是學科本身的問題
It's a question of how the teacher teaches
而是老師怎麼教的問題
Look, I saw a lot of people nodding
你看我看了很多人在點頭
right? we all suffer from it.
對不對 我們都深受其害
right
對
speak louder, yes
講大聲一點 對
and then i thought that was
然後我覺得那個是
RESPONSIBILITIES FOR OUR EXAMINATION SYSTEM
我們的考試制度的責任
Why does it make some people feel like saying
它為什麼會讓有些人覺得說
I'm not good at math, so I might as well go to school
數學不好 乾脆去念文書
wrong
錯啊
At least not in political science, and not in sociology either.
至少政治學不是這樣 社會學也不是
Why do you have to do mathematics when you read Lizhu? How can there be such a thing?
為什麼你念離主一定要數學啊?哪有這種事情?
I think it's a lot of distractions
我覺得是很多念離主的
Actually, I'm not very good at math.
其實數學也不是特別好
so there is no necessary relationship
所以沒有必然的關係
I think it's because people's lives are inherently complicated.
我是覺得說因為人的生活本來就有複雜
Sometimes we need to use specific disciplines
有些時候我們需要用到特定的學科
some specific technology this nothing
一些特定的技術 這個沒有什麼
I think of course we now reflect on
我覺得當然是我們現在反省到
Taiwan's education itself has some problems
台灣的教育本身是有一些問題
I don't know if it's a little bit better now
我不知道現在是不是稍微會好一點
or more serious i don't know
還是更嚴重我不知道
listen to your opinion
聽一下你的意見
Then I will talk about this place first today
那我今天就先講到這個地方
because sorry for more than a little time
因為不好意思 超過一點時間
There's still a little time and I hope you can ask questions
還有一點時間 希望大家能夠提問題
Teach the player Teach the player
教牌手 教牌手
Ask Professor Lin
請教林教授
ask one about that
請教一個那個有關
host
主持人
practice until you can
練到你才可以
I would say
我會說
Excuse me
不好意思
Ask you something about politics
請教你一個有關政治方面的
continue
繼續
How accurate are the polls about our current elections in Taiwan?
有關於我們台灣目前選舉的民調準確性有多高
I should recommend you the paper I wrote
我應該推薦你我寫的paper
Comparing the Accuracy Obtained by Different Survey Methods
比較不同的調查方法得到的準確性
very very accurate
非常非常準確
I will tell you a little story
我跟各位講一個小故事
Last year's nine-in-one election
去年的九合一選舉
We made a very simple game
我們做了一個很簡單的遊戲
We asked three groups of people to do the polls before the election
我們有請三組人來做民調 在選前
Then ask them to write down how many votes Ke Wenzhe will get
然後請他們把柯文哲會拿到多少的選票寫下來
Write it down and ask them to seal it
寫下來以後請他們封好了
then send me
然後寄給我
and then announced after election
然後再選後揭曉
it's interesting
這很有趣吧
it's an interesting experiment
這是一個很有趣的實驗
Then, of course, the predictions of the three people are all over 52%.
然後當然三個人的預測都是超過52%
is correct
是正確的
But there is a group where he conducts polls
可是有一組他是做民意調查的
then i was taken aback
那我嚇了一跳
I was at the time we had a sort of speech
我那時候我們開了一個有點像是演講
just three people here
就請三個人在這邊
I am the host
我當主持人
i don't know what the answer is
我也不知道答案是什麼
I only see one person laughing
我只看著有一個人在笑
should be very accurate
應該是很準
Once opened, almost the same
一打開 幾乎一樣
how does he do
他怎麼做
The question we have to ask is how does he
我們要問的問題是他怎麼做
He was clearly before the election
他明明在選前
That means polls can no longer be released
就是說已經不能發布民調
Then he used his method
然後他用他的方法
He just used traditional polling methods
他就是用傳統的民意調查方法
He goes to political map
他去做政治版圖
he didn't spend a lot of money
他也沒有花很多錢
but his answer
可是他的答案
when it is opened
一揭開的時候
clap your hands again
大家再拍手
Because the representative said it was really accurate
因為代表說真的很準
because of last year's election
因為去年的選舉
not a good election to predict
不是一個好預測的選舉
We know Ke Wenzhe will probably win
我們知道柯文哲大概會贏
But I didn't expect him to win so much
可是沒有想他贏那麼多
And he not only predicts the polls
而且他不但預測民調
is almost killing two percentage points
是幾乎殺兩個百分點
That is to say, it seems to be 57.9 and 57.7
就是說好像是57.9跟57.7
so close
差一點點
Then he connects each constituency
然後他連每一個選區的
Turnout was exactly as predicted
投票率都預測的一模一樣
almost the final answer
幾乎就是最後的答案
how did he do it
他怎麼做到
Then he did something on the spot
然後他當場就做了一件事情
He said
他說
Now everyone knows that polls can be pretty accurate
現在大家知道民意調查可以很準
will you do the poll with me
你會不會跟我一起做民調
nobody
沒有人
I do not know why
我不知道為什麼
It should be a good business
應該這個是一個很好的生意
Because he needs a lot of people to help him poll
因為他需要很多人來幫他做民調
Finally, someone said
結果好不容易有一個人說
I can come and try
我可以來試試看
His teacher must be very good at earth science
他那個老師一定很地球科學
anyway
anyway
Then the politics students don't know what you're doing
然後政治系的學生不知道你在幹什麼
In fact, polls can be very accurate
其實民調可以做得很準
Then that teacher is a teacher in the Department of Politics
然後那個老師是政治系的老師
So I think the polls must have a way
那所以我覺得民調一定有方法
That is to say, how do you pump the pressure?
就是說你要怎麼樣去抽壓
Then how do you get your answer
然後你要有什麼方法得到你的答案
absolutely impossible to call
絕對不可能打電話
It shouldn't be that simple
應該是沒有那麼簡單
You call and ask him who you want to support
你打電話問他說你要支持誰
not so simple
沒有那麼簡單
Let him do the political map
讓他做政治版圖
That is to say, you have to look at each constituency
就是說你要看每一個選區
who did he vote for
他以前投誰
Then you have to weight
然後你要加權
then you just ask
然後你只要去問
OK
OK
The result is very clear
那結果是非常的清楚
And I know his predictions are right every time
而且我知道他的預測每次都很準
so I can report a thing to
所以我就可以跟報告一件事情
Polls can be accurate
民調可以很準
But it's not the polls you hear all the time
可是不是你一天到晚聽到那些民調
Just use that as a reference
那個就參考就好了
he has a little fun
他有一點趣味
But there are actually people polling
但是真的有人在做民調
he may not let you know
他可能不會讓你知道
Come
來
joke
開玩笑
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
i feel like i want
我特別覺得我想要
Come
來
of
的
fact area of ​​objective experience
客觀經驗的事實區
make decisions
進行決策
But the source of decision-making power
但是決策的權力來源
Is it normal Italian in general?
是不是一般來講普通意大利
The Genetic Facts of the Common Italian in Tradition
傳統來講普通意大利的基因事實
then this is us
那這就是我們
Where modern stereotypes find it unscientific
現代刻板印象上覺得它不科學的地方
Because the modern age has changed
因為當代這個有變革
What do you think is science
你覺得什麼叫科學
not saying what i feel
不是說我覺得什麼
But generally our current mainstream stereotypes
可是一般我們現在主流的刻板印象
It seems that science is more like
好像覺得科學都比較像
Physics and Mathematics
物理數學那類
It is more empirically verifiable
是比較經驗性可以驗證
do you think physics is science
你覺得物理學是科學嗎
It's all science
其實都是科學
What is the core concept of physics
物理學最核心的概念是什麼
It's just some meaning of philosophy
就是一些哲學的一些意思
have you ever seen an atom
你有看過原子嗎
no i'm kidding
沒有 我在開玩笑
mean to say
意思就是說
Actually, let's talk about modern politics
其實現在講說現代的政治
there are many parts
有很多的部分
some part is to talk to voters
有一些部分是要跟選民
for votes
爭取選票的
that's called a public servant
那個叫公職人員
That's a lot of bureaucrats
那可是還有一大部分是官僚
the bureaucracy itself
那官僚系統本身
It is the industry of a modern country
就是一個現代國家的產業
you will find that many people
你就會發現說很多人
His position will not be because of whom
他的職位不會因為誰
change in power
執政就變動
OK
OK
so i think you should watch
所以我覺得你要看
which department of the government
是政府的哪一個部門
Actually I feel modern
其實我覺得現代
part of the bureaucracy is very precise
官僚體系它有一部分是非常的精準
it knows what its subjects think
它了解它的施政的對象到底在想什麼
Because now especially in the era of social media
因為現在特別是在social media的時代
There are a lot of ways that they can learn what people are thinking
他們透過很多這種方法可以了解大家在想什麼
It's just that the biggest problem with the bureaucracy is that
只是說官僚體系最大的問題在於說
they probably know it's the right thing to do
他們也許知道這件事情是對的
dare not speak to him
跟他不敢講
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
This is a problem with the political system itself
這個是政治體系本身的問題
that is to say some politicians
就是說有一些政治人物
Let's just talk about it, Shi An Fa
我們就講說好啦 實安法
Are you sure that's the only version?
你確定那個就是唯一的版本嗎
No, but why did this version pass in the end?
不是啊 可是為什麼最後會通過這個版本
This is a matter of legislative politics
這個是本身立法政治的問題
There are many elements in politics
就政治有很多的成分
There are some ingredients that they don't care about at all
有一些成分其實他們完全沒有在care這種事情
They just make it acceptable
他們只要讓大家能夠接受
their argument is fine
他們argument就好了
But there are still some of them
可是還是有一些他們
Because a very important condition for your modern country to run is
因為你現代國家要去run一個很重要的條件是
you must know
你必須知道
Let's say we're going to talk
比如說我們去講
Guest writer, he is going to the ruling platform, not the ruling
客文者他要去統治台不是統治
he's going to manage
他要去管理
To him it's domination
對他來講叫統治啦
He is going to manage Taipei City
他要去管理台北市
the purpose behind him
他後面的那個目的
very important
非常的重要
I give a simple example
我舉個簡單的例子
For example, he set up a bus stand
比如說他設公車立牌
Just to tell you what time it is
就是告訴你幾點幾分來
that is definitely not an easy thing
那個絕對不是一件簡單的事情
definitely not an easy thing
絕對不是一件簡單的事情
For example, he said that there is a charge for parking now.
還有比如說他說現在停車要收費
It's definitely not an easy thing
也絕對不是簡單的事情
He's going to do a thorough investigation on that one.
他那個都要做滿精確的調查
only possible
才有可能
That is to say, there is this characteristic
那就說有這一個特性
But with some governments he may
但是有一些政府他可能就
I don't pay much attention to this
不是很重視這一塊
But I think democracy is a
可是我覺得民主政治一個
The good thing is he can make that
好的地方是他可以讓那個
Does not rely on modern technology
不依賴現代科技
Then the reign of chaos will come down one day
然後亂統治的總有一天會下來了
or his party
或是他的政黨
I want to ask a question is
我想問一個問題就是
ask the teacher here
問老師這邊
i ask a question
我問一個問題就是說
what you just said
你剛剛講的那個
about statistic
有關於statistic
Does this statistic include it?
那這個statistic他有沒有包含
so-called information
所謂資料的會
know how to draw
會圖啊
including taking pictures
包括拍照
including control over the number of merging
包括對於合流數目的控制
I think this is also a statistic
我想這樣子來講的話也是一個statistic
as a game
作為一個game的話
He has to understand such a distribution
他必須要理解這樣的一個分布
Then this theory can be considered as this
那這個theory請問也算是這個
Are you within the scope of today's discussion?
您今天討論範圍之內嗎
Or even including Ling Nai to formulate this notoriety law
或者還有就是包括靈耐去制定這個惡名法也是
He put all this plant except Sweden
他把所有除了瑞典以外的這個植物
All controlled by his notoriety
全部用他的惡名法來把控制住了
Then this definitely has very accurate statistic information
那這個絕對有很精準的statistic information
That is, two things never had the same name.
也就是兩種東西不曾有同樣的命名
When the third type appears, the
出現第三種的時候要把
So from the game you just talked about
所以這樣的從您剛剛講的一個賽局
Spread all the way to species dispersal to map
一直擴散到物種擴散到地圖的繪製
ask the teacher something like this
請問老師這樣的一個東西
Is there any discussion in political science? Thank you
在政治學裡面有沒有探討謝謝
should say so
應該這樣講就是說
Our political science is no longer directly dealing with this issue
我們政治學現在已經不是直接處理這個問題
But I think for a modern country
但是我覺得對現代國家來講
very important thing
非常重要的事情
Do you know one thing
大家知不知道一件事情
When Japan colonized Taiwan
日本在殖民台灣的時候
who will he send first
他先派什麼樣的人來
two kinds of scholars
兩種學者
The first was an anthropologist
第一個是人類學者
The second one is I don't know what academic
第二個是我不知道是什麼學者
but he botanist
但是他植物學者
That is to say
也就是說
When the Japanese ruled Taiwan
日本人他統治台灣的時候
He did two very important things
他做了兩件非常重要的事情
For a modern country
對一個現代國家來講
everyone has interaction
每個人都有互合
Every number gets better
每一個數都有變好
Do you understand what I mean?
大家了解我的意思嗎
Only when he understands who he controls
只有當他了解他控制了誰
and where do these people live
然後這些人住在什麼地方
how many natural resources
然後有多少自然資源
he is more sure
他才比較有把握
because he is an outsider
因為他是一個外來者
so you'll find that a lot of things are said
所以你會發現說很多事情
he did it very thoroughly
他做得非常的徹底
That's statistics
那這個就是統計學
That is to say, how do you make
就是說你要怎麼樣去讓
you in a short time
你在很短的時間當中
A system capable of setting up an account
能夠建立一個戶口的系統
You will let the land you control
你會讓你控制的這一塊土地上
Every number slowly gets better
每一個數慢慢慢慢都有變好
he must be very thorough
他一定是非常徹底的
are you doing these things
在做這些事情嗎
OK, of course it means you're going to research
OK 當然就是說你要去研究
This is actually the history of statistics
這是其實統計史
How does it start with something like this
它一開始怎麼做這樣的事情
Then you find out that Japanese people do things like
然後你會發現說日本人做這樣的事情
he didn't invent it himself
也不是他自己發明
Europeans do it
歐洲人本來就這樣做
Europeans are going to occupy other places
歐洲人要去佔領別的地方
occupy elsewhere
佔領別的地方
he should know before
的之前他應該要了解
character of the place he occupies
他佔領的地方的特性
you just asked a lot of questions
那你剛剛問到很多問題
is a later development
是後來的發展
Of course it was impossible to take pictures at that time
那個時候當然不可能照相
OK that 1663
OK 那個1663年
you don't have a camera yet
你還沒有照相機啦
some jokes
有的開玩笑
I say but images are very important
我說但是圖像非常的重要
Because we know that a statistical graph
因為我們知道說一個統計的圖
A lot of Equation than you
比你一大堆Equation
much better effect
效果要好很多
Because the picture can be understood by everyone
因為圖大家可以看得懂
OK although a graph appears
OK 雖然一個圖的出現
There may be a lot of inferences behind
可能後面要一大堆的推論
but i think
但是我覺得
A very important purpose of statistics is to
統計學有一個非常重要的目的是
Let the average person know what adjustments you are making
讓一般人可以知道你在做什麼調整
So statistics has many, many components
所以統計學有很多很多的成分
There's a big part of it that we don't understand
有一大部分的成分是我們不懂的
But there must be some parts
可是一定也有一些部分是
For example, let's go to the official information now
比如說我們現在去看官方的資料
there must be some statistics
一定有一些統計資料
that as long as you go online now
那個只要你現在上網
Probably can be downloaded
大概都可以download下來
For example it must have this part
比如說它一定有這個部分
is to allow you to find the information you want
是讓你可以去找到你要的訊息
Then I would say that for everyone
那我會覺得說對各位來講
You must at least know how to calculate the average
你至少要知道怎麼算平均值
At least know how to calculate Medium
至少要知道怎麼去算Midium
that's fine
這就很好
This is called narrative statistics
這個叫敘述統計
That is to say, give you a bunch of numbers
就是說給你一堆數字
you know which number is most likely
你知道最可能的是哪一個數字
what is possible
那什麼叫可能
that's an interesting question
這就是一個有趣的問題
What do you think is all the numbers add up
你覺得是所有的數字加起來
divided by its observed value
除以它的觀察值嗎
still watching obsession
還是看迷戀
This itself is a controversial issue
這本身是一個有爭議的問題
that's why i say
所以我才會說
Statistics must have this part
統計學一定有這個部分
but of course that means
但是當然就是說
The country should be doing this now
現在國家應該是要這樣做了
But it can also have some consequences
可是它也有可能會產生一些後果
Because it's the shape of technology
因為它是科技的體型
ok you do
ok 你這樣做
maybe its consequences you don't want
也許它的後果是你不想的
Especially when it's not a democratic society
特別是它不是一個民主社會的時候
ok
ok
anymore question
還有什麼問題
still have a question
還有一個問題
you sign up
你報名
yes
對啊
good
好
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精彩的演講
Then what I want to ask is what you just introduced
那我想請教的是剛才你介紹
the place where the scholar was known
那個背識這位學者的地方
You said he was a pastor and you mentioned that he was
你就他是牧師 然後有提到他說就是
Cooking itself God himself has no way of knowing
上廚本身上帝本人沒有辦法知道
but you can see what he wants you to see
但是你可以看到他想讓你看到的東西
So the question that comes to my mind is
所以我想到的問題是
Doesn't that mean if God wants us to see a certain part
那不就代表如果上帝想讓我們看到的是某一個部分
Then we can only live forever as he wants us to see
那我們永遠只能活在他想讓我們看到
So in other words, Lin Gang also mentioned Sherlock Holmes
所以換言之 林剛也提到福爾摩斯
As long as the criminal can make Sherlock Holmes
只要罪犯能夠讓福爾摩斯
only see what he wants him to see
只看到他想讓他看到的
It is impossible for Holmes to discover the truth
福爾摩斯也不可能發現真相
this is a very good question
這是一個非常好問
So recite the information left behind
所以背識留下來的資料
Or have subsequent researchers explored
或是說後繼的研究者有沒有探討過
is it possible
有沒有可能有
It's that we can never know what we're looking at
就是我們永遠不可能知道我們在看的模題
What do you think about this in the theory of back knowledge?
那背識的理論裡面對這個有什麼看法
Great, I think this is a very, very critical question
很好 我覺得這是一個非常非常關鍵的問題
The first criminal's evidence is all here
第一個罪犯的證據都在座上
OK so a detective's job isn't that complicated
OK 所以一個偵探他的工作其實沒有那麼複雜
You just have to be able to see tiny evidence
你只要能夠看到微小的證據
you can make many inferences
你可以做很多推論
This problem is relatively simple
這個問題比較簡單
But you now know why the base
可是你現在知道為什麼那個base
comboxbase it doesn't write its stats
comboxbase它沒有寫它的統計學
it writes theology
它寫神學
the problem is very complicated
問題非常的複雜
about what god can show you
就上帝到底可以讓你看到什麼
that is a theological question
那是一個神學的問題
Of course for a Christian
當然對一個基督徒來講
for him
對他來講
God will never let you see things that will make you feel scared
上帝一定不會讓你看到會覺得很恐懼的事情
but how do you know it's true
可是你怎麼知道這件事情是真的
that is a theological question
那是一個神學的問題
So there is a law that can be derived from its back
所以有一個可以從它的背式的法則當中
find a clue that says
找到一個線索就是說
God will show you one thing
上帝會讓你看到一件事情
not for you to see once
不是讓你看一次
it will make you watch it many times
它會讓你看很多次
and not just for you to see
而且不是只有讓你看
it allows everyone to see
它可以讓每一個人看
know what i mean
了解我的意思嗎
That is to say, this rule is applicable to everyone.
就是說這個法則是每一個人都可以用的
If everyone can use this law to deduce
如果大家都可以用這個法則去推論
Isn't this the best way?
那這個不是最好的方法嗎
if the work of moose
如果說穆斯的工作
Just to tell everyone what God is
就是要把上帝是什麼告訴大家
So it actually has a theological purpose
所以它其實它有一個神學的目的
but i think it makes sense
但是我覺得它有它的道理
That means
那就是說
This thing is different from statistics after the 19th century
這個東西跟十九世紀以後的統計學是不一樣的
The statistics after the four seasons are probably very fixed
就四季以後的統計學大概就很固定
Statistics has several basic assumptions
統計學它有幾個基本的假定
From these assumptions it can then be deduced that
然後根據這些假定可以推論出
what is the best statistical model
什麼是最好的統計模型
But like it doesn't come like this
可是類似它不是這樣來的
It is based on Prior belief
它是根據Prior belief
What is Prior belief?
什麼叫Prior belief
anything can
什麼都可以
But the point is you can always renew your beliefs
但是重點是你可以一直更新你的信念
So the point is to keep updating
所以重點是一直更新
It's not an update, it's an update all the time
不是更新是一直更新
Hello, I read Li Ke
你好 我是念李科的
It's hard
好不容易啊
Get some enlightenment in this topic today
今天在這個題目裡面得到一些啟蒙
In the past, I only heard that gorgeousness values ​​fairness and justice.
以前只聽說華麗重視的是公平正義
What economics focuses on is efficiency
那經濟學重視的是效率
that politics is a series of compromises
那政治是一連串的妥協
Then today I finally saw the original in the compromise
那今天總算在妥協裡面看到原來
it has a statistical background
它有統計的背景
And there is some basis for this competition theory
而且還有一些這個賽舉理論的根據
So the question I want to ask is
那我想要問的問題是
Today the teacher mentioned that
今天老師有提到說
Since it is an electoral system, it will affect the distribution of the entire political party
既然是選舉制度會影響到整個政黨的分布
then if we go back to
那如果我們回到
If politics is just strategy itself
如果說政治它只是策略的本身
there is a purpose behind it
背後有一個目的存在
Let's go back to Taiwan
那回歸到台灣來講
Taiwan is a multicultural society
台灣是一個多元文化的社會
In such a multicultural society, we can't afford the old-fashioned infighting over there.
這樣多元文化社會其實我們經不起老式在那邊內耗
Based on the principle of no internal friction, it should be avoided that the two parties are just doing a rotation over there.
那基於不內耗的原則應該要避免只是兩黨在那邊做一個輪替而已
Is that in the electoral system? I don't know from a political point of view.
那是不是在選舉制度裡面我不曉得從政治學的角度
Is it true that Taiwan is also going to be like a Huaguo?
是不是台灣是不是也要走向化國那樣子
Will there be more cooperation with the party?
才會讓跟黨之間比較多的合作呢
It's a little too late for you to ask the question
你是問題要問的有點太晚了
because it's too late
因為已經來不及了
no i'm kidding
沒有,我是開玩笑的
Why, because why is there such an electoral system now, have you ever wondered
為什麼,因為現在為什麼會有這種選舉制度,你有沒有想過
Yes, why is it ordered by the big party, because he hates the small party
對啊,為什麼是大黨訂出來的,因為他討厭小黨
Talking about the Wenxian here is that you talk about those who oppose the system
講這邊的文憲是你把那個反對制度的就是講
So is there going to be Wenxian who has a lot of Wenxian love here?
所以講這邊會不會有多文憲情的文憲
In fact, he has a point, that is, I don't have time to talk about institutional theory today.
其實他有一種,就是說我今天沒有時間講制度論
Because if you really talk about it, sometimes it will be very sad.
因為你真的講下去有些時候會很悲哀的
Because of some systems he is a minority
因為有些制度他是少數人
It's not a few people, it's a certain group of people. After it is established, it will be standardized.
不是少數人他是某一些人訂出來以後,他就有規範性
If you don't do this, no, you won't have a seat
那你不這樣做,不行,你就沒有席次
So he will be very unfair to the third force or other minor parties
所以他會對第三勢力或其他的小黨很不公平
But then it's like you're talking about politics compromising
但後來就像你講政治在妥協
Why didn't he set a single constituency with two votes?
他為什麼沒有定成單一選區兩票制
pure unitary constituency
純粹的單一選區制
Because we still have party-white negotiations
因為我們還有黨白協商
Xiaodang said it can't be done like this
小黨說不能這樣定
He said that if you can't set the joint force system in Germany
他說你如果不能定成德國的聯力制
At least make a case
好歹定一個病例制
What does case system mean
病例制是什麼意思
Even if you still have part of the country
就是你還是有全國部分區
Little party still has a chance
小黨還是有機會
In other words, when will the small party have a chance
也就是說小黨什麼時候會有機會
When the strength of your two major parties is about the same
當你兩大黨的實力差不多的時候
small party will have some chance
小黨會有一些機會
But the problem is because it's leisure
但是問題是因為這是休閒
Leisure is a super high threshold
休閒是超高的門檻
everyone should know
大家應該知道
More than three-quarters of Congress agree
國會四分三以上的同意
then to
然後要
almost impossible
幾乎不可能
when electing president
選總統的時候
More than half of the electorate turned out to vote
一半以上的選民出來投票
is possible to pass
才有可能通過
So it's impossible if he didn't tie the election
所以如果他沒有綁大選根本不可能
But you say it's impossible
但你說不可能嘛也不見得
I'll see
我就看情況了
We can only say that now Taiwan
我們只能說現在台灣的
The threshold for system reform is very high
這個制度改革的門檻很高
Then this threshold was set in 2005
然後這個門檻就是2005年定出來的
not yet
還不行
That's all I can say, that's all I can say as a scholar
我只能這樣講 做一個學者只能這樣講
Well, I think of course there are many ways.
那我覺得當然還有很多方法啦
But now that we have a system
但是我們現在既然有一個制度
Everyone is using this system
大家都在用這個制度了
I think it's better to follow it
我覺得還是照著它走會比較好一點
anymore question
還有什麼問題
right
對
Yeah
對對對
EITM
EITM喔
Because we now sometimes have to create some nouns
因為我們現在有些時候要創造一些名詞
it does not omit at all
它一點都不省略
EITM就是Imperial Implications of Theoretical Models
EITM就是Imperial Implications of Theoretical Models
Imperial Implications of Theoretical Models
Imperial Implications of Theoretical Models
is the empirical implication of your theoretical model
是你的理論模型的經驗意涵
it speaks vernacular
它講白話文
for example
比如說
it has a theory, right?
它有個理論 對嗎
Give me a test, that's what it means
給我測看看 就這個意思
Just say you want Imperial Implications
就說 你要Imperial Implications
sounds deep, doesn't it
聽起來很深號對不對
It's what you test
它就是你測看看嘛
what to test test me and theory
測什麼東西 測我和理論
It's called Theoretical Models
就叫Theoretical Models
That is, your model is not just a model
就是你的model還不只是一個model
It's from Theoretic
它是從Theoretic來的
For example, we just talked about Divacient
比如說我們剛剛講Divacient
Is a Theoretical Models
就是一個Theoretical Models
Front it has Theoretic
前面它有Theoretic
wired at the back
後面有線
help him change it to MODE
幫他把它變成MODE
can detect
就可以檢測
What is detected?
檢測什麼呢?
right or wrong
對 還是不對
So it is IMPIRICLE
所以它是IMPIRICLE
it is an empirical test
它是經驗性的檢測
So EITM sorry
所以EITM抱歉
Because of this in political science has become a JACAN
因為這個在政治學已經變成一個JACAN
Because I feel that POWPON
因為我覺得那個POWPON
I can't fit so many words
塞不下這麼多字
it's not mysterious at all
它其實一點都不神秘
there's nothing wrong with it
它沒有什麼問題
no problem
沒有問題
time has come
時間已經到
i want to clarify one thing
我要澄清一件事情
That's what Mr. Lin said just now
就是剛才林老師說
like in the future
將來喜歡的
I do not know him
我不認識他
But because when he was studying, he
但是因為讀書的時候他
In fact, when I was studying
其實我讀書的時候
I help my wife with reading
我幫我太太過讀書
but i haven't seen either
但是我也沒見過
then like in the future
那麼將來喜歡的
He and I are around there
跟我他都在那附近
I don't even remember coming with me in the hallway
我都不記得我在走廊跟我來
Always
一直
but i'm not
但是我並不是
I didn't come to talk about anything
我當時並不是來談什麼
because he waited for me to come back
因為他等我回來講
yes i have graduated
是我已經畢業了
After returning to Taiwan
回台灣以後
one hour later
一段時間以後
but before he died
不過他過世之前
We had a teacher tell me
我們有一個老師跟我講
he not long ago
他不久前
i am on campus
我在校園
You see a continent
你們看到有個大陸的
19 photos taken together
19個那合照
beat him up
被他揍了一圈
He probably didn't really take a beating
他大概不是真的是揍一圈
probably him
大概就是他
it's this special person
就是這個特別的人
Look at the features
看特點
He doesn't want people on the water level
他不希望人家在水平面
Scared him on the way
在路上就來嚇他了
yes
沒錯
So I pushed it around
所以大概推了一圈
As a result, he soon became an economist
結果過不久就他就做經濟
When I received a big prize to do business
領了一個大獎做經濟的時候
From Canada Airport
從Canada Airport
When it's time to go back to Briston
到要回布里斯頓的時候
died in a car accident
車禍死了
But there was a mathematician who colonized the world
但是有一位世界殖民的數學家
I can't tell if he is
我不能講他是不是
He was also a professor in Princeton's Department of Mathematics
他也曾經在普林斯特的數學系當過教授
he told me
他告訴我
he will think
他將他想
if he was joking
如果他是開玩笑
I told him
我告訴他
he said
他說啊
If you don't get that prize
如果沒有領那個大獎
probably won't die
大概就不會死
he because we from
他因為我們從
from that airport
從那個Airport
back to princeton
回到普林斯頓
Are doing Airport
都是做Airport
Just a dozen people do it
就是十幾個人做
Eighty and thirty yuan per person
一個人八十塊三十塊
those are poor
那些很窮
Don't even talk about how much money you don't have
都不要講沒有多少錢
yes then what
對 然後呢
How is he willing to spend 350 dollars
他怎麼願意花350美金
do that economy
做那個經濟
probably
大概就是
got that
得了那個
Said that he is still proportional to 10 people
說他還比例10人
8 times everyone
8倍有大家
so what
所以呢
money again
又錢了
So do 350
所以做了350
3 400 mass momentum
3 400塊的機運
Involuntary movement vehicle
免機的機運車錢
So this one took him
所以這一座就把他
life is dead
生活就死掉了
that
那個
Everyone is interested to see
大家有興趣看
His book should have Chinese Art Edition
他的書應該有中藝本
beautiful
美麗的
he is very legendary
他是非常傳奇
very very interesting
非常非常有趣
There is a movie version
有電影版
The movie version is not allowed
電影版不準
At least that Rossel Coro doesn't look like it at all
至少那個Rossel Coro也一點都不像
OK OK
好了好了
very very thank you all
非常非常謝謝大家
very exciting today
今天非常精彩
Thanks
謝謝